<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox militis foreshewing what perils are procured where the people of this, or any other kingdome liue without regard of marshall discipline, especially when they stand and behold their friends in apparent danger, and almost subuerted by there enemies vniust persecution, and yet with hold their helping hand and assistance. Diuided into two parts, the first manifesting for what causes princes may enter into warre, and how necessary and vsuall it is, drawne from the actions of the Prince of Orange. The second discourseth of warre, souldiers, and the time when it is conuenient: collected out of the heroicall examples of Count Mansfield. ... Dedicated to Count Mansfield, and the honourable Councell of Warre.</title>
            <author>Marcelline, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851107</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851107</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1185:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox militis foreshewing what perils are procured where the people of this, or any other kingdome liue without regard of marshall discipline, especially when they stand and behold their friends in apparent danger, and almost subuerted by there enemies vniust persecution, and yet with hold their helping hand and assistance. Diuided into two parts, the first manifesting for what causes princes may enter into warre, and how necessary and vsuall it is, drawne from the actions of the Prince of Orange. The second discourseth of warre, souldiers, and the time when it is conuenient: collected out of the heroicall examples of Count Mansfield. ... Dedicated to Count Mansfield, and the honourable Councell of Warre.</title>
                  <author>Marcelline, George.</author>
                  <author>Rich, Barnabe, 1540?-1617. Allarme to England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 58 [i.e. 56], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By B[ernard] A[lsop] for Thomas Archer, and are to bee sold at his shop in Popes head Alley, ouer against the signe of the Horse-shoe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: G.M., i.e. George Marcelline.</note>
                  <note>An adaptation of "Allarme to England" by Barnabe Rich. Much of the book exactly reprints Rich's work; Marcelline omits passages relating to contemporary events, replacing them with others of a similar nature.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In this state the first quire has four leaves.</note>
                  <note>P. 56 misnumbered 58.</note>
                  <note>The last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>War --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Armed forces --  Management --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:1"/>
            <p>VOX MILITIS: FORESHEWING WHAT PERILS ARE PROCVRED WHERE THE people of this, or any other kingdome liue without regard of Marſhall diſcipline, eſpecially when they ſtand and behold their friends in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent danger, and almoſt ſubuerted by there enemies vniuſt perſecution, and yet with hold their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Diuided into two parts, the firſt manifeſting for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cauſes Princes may enter into warre, and how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and vſuall it is, drawne from the actions of the Prince of Orange. The ſecond diſcourſeth of warre, ſouldiers, and the time when it is conuenient: <hi>collected out of the heroicall examples of Count</hi> MANSFIELD.</p>
            <p>Where, as in a mirrour, meet to be peruſed by Kings, Princes, Nobles, Knights, Gentlemen, and men of all degrees throughout the whole kingdome, to behold with what conſideration they ſhould firſt enter into the warre, with what cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage they ſhould proſecute them, and how to deale with a common Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dedicated to Count Mansfield, and the honourable Councell of Warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>B. A.</hi> for THOMAS ARCHER, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, ouer againſt the ſigne of the Horſe-ſhoe. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:2"/>
            <head>ILLVSTRISSIMO HONORATISSIMO NOBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LISSIMOQVE DOMINO ERNESTO <hi>Mansfieldiae,</hi> Comiti, Marchioni Caſtelli noui &amp; maximi exercitus Duci, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>LLVSTRISSIME Princeps (vere non blande ſic te appellem) quitam virtutum quam rerum polles claritate, acre militari tum Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te vt aiunt, tum Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curio longe ſuperas, quem natura non tanquam dura Nouerca, quin potius Charamater, non ſolum bello Strenuum at conſilio ſapientem conſtituit, vt prius timorem poſterius temeritatem abs te ferret, ac certe vtrum mens an manus ſit forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or dictu difficillimum videtur: Neque quid miri dignitati tuae ſit, qua cauſa ductus hoc o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus aut potius opuſculum bellicoſum tibi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum dedicarem? quandoquidem tu dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimus Miles (pene dixiſſem militum Atlas) merito habearis: qui ficut alter Hercules vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantes
<pb facs="tcp:16363:3"/>ac in alienas poſſeſſiones ruentes Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos pia mente &amp; potenti manu penitus euerte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re conaris. Quis igitur melior de bello tractatus Patronus? quam qui in bello tractat, quis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior amicus erit libro cuius ſubiectum bellum quam ipſe vir qui eſt ſubiectum belli? Preterea ſicut armis, ſic etiam artibus ſemper non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum beneuolentiae oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſti, &amp; muſarum ſeruis non ſolum amicus amictus victus, ſed etiam ipſa vita, ab in eunte fuiſti aetate, deinde quam gratus pleriſque Britaniae acceſſus tuus eſt ex corum oculis &amp; vultibus qui ſunt indices ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi facillime colligas, inter quos ego mediocre non concipiens gaudium ac nihil habens, quo aduentum tuum gratuler niſi hos ingenij mei &amp; laboris fructus quos honori tuo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cro: parum dubitans immo confidenter ſperans quod ſicut ex amore more &amp; officio ſunt ſupra Altare, pluſquam humanae bonitatis tuae impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiti. Sic erunt tanquam gratum ſacrificium ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepti, &amp; ſereno accipies &amp; aſpicies fronte, in quibus legitimum immo neceſſarium belli v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum militum varios iniquos tum equos mores, ſimiliter tempusad bellum gerendum oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunum, &amp; militaris diſciplinae exercitium cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas.</p>
            <p>Quae ſi perleges parum pertimeſco, (ſi modo
<pb facs="tcp:16363:3"/>ſine Philautia dieam) quin ex hoc officioſo ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a me tibi oblato, non minus vtilitatis quam voluptatis capies: exoptans ita<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> dignitati tuae ſummam (aut ſi quae ſumma ſit ſuperior) foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem in conſcientia pacem in bello victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, vtcunque internam, externam, &amp; aeternam valetudinem in omne aeuum maneo.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tuarum virtutum obſeruantiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, <hi>G. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE and noble fauourer of all Vertue and Learning, OLIVER, Viſcount <hi>Grandiſon,</hi> One of the <hi>Councell of Warre in Great</hi> BRITAINE.</head>
            <p>RIGHT Honourable, and truely Noble, as well famous for all vertues in generall, as valour in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: There is no worke can be ſo worthy, but in this mimike and Spleenſike age, it is ready euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be rackt vpon the racke of a harſh cenſure, but moſt eſpecially ſuch as write any thing in the defence of thoſe ſo much perſecuted profeſſions, as the Scholler and the Souldier, the which though none pittie them for their pouerty, yet moſt men enuy for their worth the one, becauſe they can not attaine vnto it: The other, becauſe they dare not bee of it, it is not then to be hoped for: But this my Treatiſe will meete with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny calumnies, and the voyce of the Souldier will haue many ſoggy miſty vapour, which breath proceeding from malicious mouths, will ſeeke to preuent the paſſage of it: the couetous Carle, who makes his gold his gold, cries out againſt it, and cannot endure ſo much as the Eccho of it, he ſayes it is ſo chargeable, and he had rather indanger his perſon, then indammage his purſe: Another is ſo loath to leaue his Miſtreſſe to find out honour, that the very voyce ſeemes to him as thunder, and he cannot ſuffer it; another hath bathed himſelfe ſo long in the ſun-ſhine of peace, as this ſtorme goes to the heart of him, in ſo much as theſe my labours are like to encounter with many aduerſaries, and this Treatiſe of Warre, to haue a multitude of warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours againſt it, it is forced therefore to ſeek to ſhelter it ſelf vnder the wings of your protection, whereby it may be preſerued from the ſury of all the foes, and enuious darts of all the deſpiſers of it. The reaſon why I commend
<pb facs="tcp:16363:4"/>it to your Honours tuition, and become an earneſt and humble ſuter to your Honor for your patronage: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, is in regard I hope you will ſomewhat reſpect it for the names ſake you are chiefly elected of the King, as the moſt experienc't ſoldiours of this Kingdome to be of his Counſell of warre, and this is the voyce of a Souldiour which doth concord with your Counſell, being as an Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, to awake all men out of the ſlumber of Securitie, to perſwade them neuer ſo much to deſire peace as to deteſt warre, ſeeing it is an action not onely lawfull but neceſſary to aſſume armes, either for the defence of our ſelues, or the reliefe of others, whoſe Dominions are vniuſtly detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or tirannically vſurped. Farre be it from me to be too ſaucie, as to offer to aduiſe you that were a ſinne of horrid preſumption, and as great a follie as for the feet to guide the head, or the Aſſe to Counſell the Lyon, but my intent is to inſtruct the ignorant, to awake the ſecure, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the valiant, to condemne the cowardly, to raiſe the reputation of Souldiers, who are now looked vpon with a contemptfull eye, whoſe ſoules are captiuated with want &amp; miſery, who fight faintly becauſe they are not rewarded brauely, to ſhew how in former times they which had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued themſelues valiantly were recompenſed honorably, whereas now a dayes, the meede of their deſerts for the moſt part is a bagge and a wallet, and there gayne the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes to deplore the decay of Marſhall diſcipline, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of warlike affaires, the which for a long time lay blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and were giuing vp the Ghoſt, vntill your Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Counſell recouered them and gaue vnto them life and action. Vouchſafe therefore moſt worthy Peeres to Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize this worke, and to daigne to accept of this mite caſt into your treaſury, reſpecting not the greatneſſe of the gift, but the might of the giuer, who though he can not preſent vnto you a worke according to his will, yet to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb facs="tcp:16363:5"/>of his power, whoſe onely hope is built vpon your acceptance? Oh then doe you reſpect this preſent, as God doth our petitions of whome it is ſaid,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non vox ſed votum, non muſica cordula ſed cor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non clamans ſed amans, ſonat in are Dei.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>T'is not the voice, but vow, the heart, not muſickes ſtring,</l>
                  <l>The loue, and not the cry, that in Gods eares doe ring.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Reſpect therefore in this worke, not the ſtatelineſſe of the ſtile, but the vprightneſſe of the heart, not the well pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the words, but the goodneſſe of the intent, for it is the intention that crownes the action, &amp; what better drift can there be of a mans deſignes then the weale publick, the preſernation of his Countrie, the honor of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the prouiſion of an Antidote againſt forrainefoes &amp; forces, the Centinell hath not an idle or vnneceſſary office, the watchman in the Citie is not in vaine, he that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnes his friends fore-armes them, and ſurely I thinke then, this can not diſtaſt any honeſt, though it may bee ſome curious Palates howſoeuer: Howſoeuer let me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you, nay more obtaine ſo much of your Honours, that as you are a Counſeller of Warre, ſo you would bee Countenancers of this ſouldiers voyce: that ſo by your furtherance a more happy ſucceſſe may crowne my indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoures, my labours be more fruitfull, cauſing all men to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake out of Securitie, and to be in a readineſſe to make reſiſtance againſt him that is alwayes ayming to giue an aſſault. So ſhall you ſhew your ſelues to be worthie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers of Warre, Comſorters of Warriers, Cauſers of the wellfare of this Kingdome, and make the Author of this worke eternally obliged vnto you, who intreateth you to accept his labours as graciouſly as he offers it officiouſly, And reſts</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>As ready in his perſon as his penne to doe his Soueraigne ſeruice, his Countrie good, and your Honours duety. G. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>VOX MILITIS:</hi> OR, An Enemy to Securitie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REmembring how the anticke Poets faign'd,</l>
               <l>The Gods did puniſh thoſe which them diſdaind:</l>
               <l>How wofull <hi>Troy</hi> in flaming fires did mourne,</l>
               <l>Cauſe <hi>Paris</hi> did the ſuite of <hi>Iuno</hi> ſcorne;</l>
               <l>How faire <hi>Narciſs</hi> into a flowre was turnd,</l>
               <l>Cauſe he at <hi>Venus</hi> dainty darlings ſpurnd:</l>
               <l>J deemd that angry <hi>Mars</hi> could doe no leſſe,</l>
               <l>Then his fell ſury vpon thoſe expreſſe;</l>
               <l>Which doe all Marſhall Diſcipline neglect,</l>
               <l>And none of his braue Paramours respect,</l>
               <l>Who let there weapons hang ſecure and ruſt,</l>
               <l>Surely it ſhould not ſeeme in him vniuſt,</l>
               <l>If he ſhould make them heauy paines endure,</l>
               <l>Which doe contemne his honour, liue ſecure:</l>
               <l>And ſo he doth as neighb'ring Kingdomes ſhow,</l>
               <l>Who by their peace nurſt vp their ouerthrow:</l>
               <l>The milke white Swan that in Meander ſwimmes,</l>
               <l>And in that Christ all floud doth bath his limmes,</l>
               <l>Did from the Crow receiue no mickell hate,</l>
               <l>Who enuide at her happy faire eſtate,</l>
               <l>And labourd by all meanes her beauty faire</l>
               <l>To ſoyle, and ſo her whiteneſſe to empaire:</l>
               <l>But all in vaine, whiles as the carefull Swan,</l>
               <l>With watchfull eye obſerud him, but whan</l>
               <l>Shee did not watch, but when as ſilent ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſion of the Swanues faire lights did keepe;</l>
               <l>Then at that houre ſhee ſate vpon her skirt,</l>
               <l>And all her white array beſmeard with dirt:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16363:6"/>
               <l>Oh let not then this our faire Swan-like Ile.</l>
               <l>All feare of future harmes from it exile,</l>
               <l>Promiſing peace, when an vnhappy fate,</l>
               <l>Is eminent vnto her enuied ſtate:</l>
               <l>Neither let thoſe, whoſe faces blacke as hell,</l>
               <l>In whoſe blacke hearts, all blacke deſignes doe dwell;</l>
               <l>Iniure her bleſt condition, neither Spaine</l>
               <l>Hinder her peace, giue life vnto her paine;</l>
               <l>I doubt not if ſhee wake, they cannot hurt her,</l>
               <l>Yet if ſhee ſlumber, they may chance bedurt her,</l>
               <l>Which to preuent, here is the Souldiers voyce</l>
               <l>Awakes for feare her foes, ſhould her deboyce:</l>
               <l>And let her Neighbours harmes, her armes be made,</l>
               <l>Let her ſole bliſſe be on their ruine laide,</l>
               <l>So iſt not fit in our Houſe ſhould befeare,</l>
               <l>When in our Neighbours fierr flames appeare,</l>
               <l>Will not the Souldier fence his proper head,</l>
               <l>When he his fellow ſeeth ſtrucken dead;</l>
               <l>Will not the Schollar to himſelfe take heede,</l>
               <l>When as the rod doth make the others bleede</l>
               <l>Conſider then how theſe thy enemies,</l>
               <l>Did forr aigne lands in ſtate ſecure ſurprize,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Antwerpes</hi> fall like thunder in thy eares,</l>
               <l>Rouze thee from ſlumber, ſummon thee to feares,</l>
               <l>Which Towne could nere haue liberty forſooke,</l>
               <l>If that her foes had not her napping tooke:</l>
               <l>So did the Greekes vnto the Towne of Troy,</l>
               <l>Which being dead in ſleepe and drinke, they did deſtroy.</l>
               <l>And as for late times, the Palatinate</l>
               <l>Through former eaſe, brought to vnhappy fate:</l>
               <l>Heare but what France of haughty Spaine can ſpeake,</l>
               <l>And it will ſlumber from your ſoules eye, breake,</l>
               <l>Examine a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Land each place on earth,</l>
               <l>Sayes danger from ſecurity hath birth;</l>
               <l>It caſie ſeemes to ſtrike a ſtanding Bucke,</l>
               <l>When as a tripping Doe hath better lucke.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16363:6"/>
               <l>The ſtauding Poole with ſpeede doth putrifie,</l>
               <l>When we no filth in running ſtreames diſcrie:</l>
               <l>All which doth manifeſt no other,</l>
               <l>Then that eaſe is of ſorrowes all the mother:</l>
               <l>Whiles <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſlept in his faire minions lap,</l>
               <l>He was yeatched in his ſtrumpets trap;</l>
               <l>Whiles <hi>Holifernes</hi> ſlept on downy bed,</l>
               <l>He loſt the ſought for conqueſt, and his head:</l>
               <l>And tis a maxime that exceſſe of reſt,</l>
               <l>Hath bad ſucceſſe, and ſild, or ueuers bleſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> can t'indure <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> ſhout,</l>
               <l>Haue all the honour from terreſtriall mould;</l>
               <l>Tis meete he ſhould haue ſome, tis againſt right,</l>
               <l>That in his worſhip man ſhould nere delight:</l>
               <l>Then ſtay no longer from God <hi>Mars</hi> his broyle,</l>
               <l>Learne to defend your ſelues, your foes to foyle:</l>
               <l>You which ſo much adord the pipe and pot,</l>
               <l>Aſcribe now worſhip to the pike and ſhot,</l>
               <l>Make <hi>Mars</hi> his Altars ſmoake, his Angels flie,</l>
               <l>Leaue luſt, and follow matchleſſe Chiualry,</l>
               <l>That ſo you may immortalize your name,</l>
               <l>And purchaſe to your ſelues eternall fame;</l>
               <l>Blunt the edge of their fury, which doe ſpight</l>
               <l>This our faire Albion, the Worlds delight:</l>
               <l>There is no honour, like to that in which</l>
               <l>One ſuffers death, to make his Countrey rich:</l>
               <l>Then on my Lads, doe not lie ſlugging heere,</l>
               <l>To ſmoake tobacco pipes, and ſucke the beere;</l>
               <l>But rather arme, and for your Countrey ſtand,</l>
               <l>Remember Honours harueſt is at hand,</l>
               <l>In which you reape renowne, if vile diſgrace,</l>
               <l>And cowardize produce not ſhame of face:</l>
               <l>Then for your armes prepare with all the ſpeede,</l>
               <l>To make Religions foes from heart to bleede,</l>
               <l>Thinke how the praiſe of an heroicke ſprite,</l>
               <l>With his Countries foes in field to fight.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16363:7"/>
               <l>For this your Worthies had their Temples crownd,</l>
               <l>And were of all this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſe renownd;</l>
               <l>In that they labourd for their Countries good,</l>
               <l>And all her forraigne Foes with force withſtood:</l>
               <l>Were, bee ſuch now, here in a chimney corner,</l>
               <l>One fellow quakes and ſhakes like <hi>Thomas Horner;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When once he heares the rumors of the Warres,</l>
               <l>He is a man of peace, and loues not iarres:</l>
               <l>Yet want and pouerty doth haunt him ſo,</l>
               <l>He knowes not where to flie, nor what to doe;</l>
               <l>Another fellow ſeemeth to applaude,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bellonas</hi> comming, and her perſon laude:</l>
               <l>But if to follow her one ſhould him trye,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Thraſo</hi> then heed in infidiis lie,</l>
               <l>As ſome in office other men doe preſſe</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the warres, when they loue nothing leſſe:</l>
               <l>And a third ſort perhaps the warres doe curſe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they doe ſuppoſe theyle charge his purſe:</l>
               <l>Another that can ſcarce endure a ſcratch,</l>
               <l>Made with his Miſtreſſe pin, when he doth catch</l>
               <l>Her by ſome part forbidden, if be heares</l>
               <l>That <hi>Mars</hi> within this Hemyſphere appeares,</l>
               <l>A palſie takes him, he ſayes hees vndone,</l>
               <l>He feares he ſhall be killed with a gun:</l>
               <l>And he another fault in them doth ſee,</l>
               <l>He feares his lodging too too hard will be.</l>
               <l>But vp baſe minde, and learne to ſoare a loft,</l>
               <l>Honour lies not vpon a bed thats ſoft,</l>
               <l>Nor worthy knowledge, to the warre make haſt,</l>
               <l>And ſtrine to get aname that ere may laſt.</l>
               <l>Now leaſt thou ſhouldſt be dull, and loath to ſtirre,</l>
               <l>Peruſe this worke of mine here as a ſpurre,</l>
               <l>To pricke thee forward, where as thou maiſt reade</l>
               <l>The worth of warres, and how they all exceede,</l>
               <l>Where thou mayſt vnderſtand a Souldier true,</l>
               <l>His labours meede that honour is his due:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16363:7"/>
               <l>And that like <hi>Atlas</hi> on his ſhoulders hee,</l>
               <l>Vpreares the Common-Wealth from dangers free.</l>
               <l>The tyme when we theſe our armes vp ſhould take</l>
               <l>The which obſeru'd the warres doth proſperous make.</l>
               <l>And fourthly, this to thee doth ſhew the way,</l>
               <l>By which doth Marſhall diſcipline decay.</l>
               <l>Then let theſe flowres which I with payne collected,</l>
               <l>Not bee with ſcornefull Eye of thee reiected.</l>
               <l>The Toyle was mine, the Pleaſure thine; the Paine</l>
               <l>Mine owne, doe thou but daygne to reape the Gaine.</l>
               <l>I like the Bee, the Hony home haue brought,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe thee but to tast that I haue ſought:</l>
               <l>Which if thou doeſt't will ſo encourage then,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt reape riper fruites from this my pen.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:16363:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16363:8"/>
            <head>VOX MILITIS, FORESHEWING WHAT PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RILLES ARE PROCVRED WHERE <hi>THE PEOPLE OF THIS OR</hi> any other kingdome, liue without regard of <hi>Marſhall Diſcipline: eſpecially, when they</hi> ſtand and behold their Neighbours and <hi>Friends in apparent daunger, &amp; almoſt</hi> deſtroyed by their enemies vniuſt <hi>perſecution, and not to aſſiſt them.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is free from all doubt or ſuſpicion that multitudes may coniecture me to haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more then ſufficient trauaile in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terp iſe: To wit, This deſcription of Warres &amp; Martiall affaires, primarily in regard that they haue euer had the eſtimation of plagues and puniſhments, and to the Palats of ſome perſons apprehenſion are ſo diſtaſtfull, that it is the moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſuperlatiue, and malignant of all miſchiefes, being aſwell accompted an affliction to the harmeleſſe as to the hurtfull, to the innocent as to the iniurious: for by it wholeſome lawes and ſalutiferous Precepts are violated, Humanity defaced, Iuſtice peruerted and ſuppreſſed, Pious places are prophaned, Horryd murthers committed, vndefiled Virgins deſloured, chaſt modeſt Matrons defiled, ſpacious Kingdomes ſubuerted, great Cities ſubdued and ruinated. As <hi>Numace</hi> admired for the valour, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> famous for the magnificence, <hi>Thebes</hi> vnparalleld for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16363:9"/>ſtatelineſſe of the building and edifices. delicate <hi>Tyre</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht, <hi>Athens,</hi> holy <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Contentious <hi>Carthage, Antwerp,</hi> and in this our moderne and miſerable age, <hi>Prague</hi> the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> and <hi>Breda</hi> now languiſhing in the like miſery, the which with diuers of her companyons by the meanes of warres haue bin ſacked and ſpoyled, robbed and ruinated, &amp; oftentimes layd waſt and deſolate, and therefore it is but meerely a puniſhment inſlicted by God, vpon ſome place for ſome notable ſinne and heauy affliction, being vſed of him as a coraſiue to eate out the dead fleſh of ſecurity, the onely meanes to humble vs for our owne ſinnes, and to reduce vs from the following of our owne corruptions to the fauouring of Chriſtian religion.</p>
            <p>A Secondary cauſe which induceth me to ſuſpect, that this my work is likely to be rackt with many a raſh cenſure, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That as it is obuious in it ſelfe: ſo it is odious in reſpect of the inſtruments which are vſed in it, as the profeſſors and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of it are in ſuch meane reſpect and eſtimation, as they are rather deemed ſit for Ruffians, Roy ſters, and people of a vile abiect condition, rather then an exerciſe for honeſt holy men of conſcionable conuerſation: who neyther beare any zeale to Gods glory, nor any affection to theyr brothers good: in ſo much as it is <hi>Cornelius Agrippas</hi> aſſertion, that if you deſire to ſee a true Tyrant, a Prophaner, or a Murtherer, a Robber, a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſher, a Deſiourer, if you would haue all theſe ſeuerall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in one ſingular perſon, and if you deſire to include all this matter in one word, it is comprehended in this one name Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</p>
            <p>But to the end we may addreſſe our Treatie to our intended Subiect, <hi>viz. WARR,</hi> becauſe I know many be ſo ſcrupulous and tender conſciences, as they deeme them abſolutely vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. I held it not fruiteleſſe and of no ſmall import and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to produce ſome proofe, aſwell out of Scripture as other wryters, to ſhew the lawfullneſſe and good approbation of Military proceedings euen by God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>I could here produce whole cloudes of Teſtymonies out of Scripture for the confirmation of the trneth of this poſition: to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16363:9"/>proue that warres haue beene acceptable before the Maieſty of God, and ſometimes of more preuailence then peace, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more cleerely, then the Meridian light, in the ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Booke of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> where the children of Iſrael were reproued, for concluding a peace with the Cananites, neither hath onely approbation by the Scriptures, but is alſo receiued as a lawfull proceeding by diuers other famous Authours, and that it is not onely conuenient, but neceſſary for Princes to make a breach of amity, that they might better make a confirmation of inuiolable friendſhip, that their loue might be like a limme which being broken and well ſet, becomes more ſtrong and ſtable; and it is a Warre moſt worthily initiated, whereby the ſecurity and ſafety of the States effected, and on the contrary that peace is not well permitted, but moſt pernicious, which is the mother and cauſer of the peoples perill, and the Countries hazard: And that true mirror of eloquence, <hi>Cicero,</hi> telles vs; <hi>Ad hunc finem bella ſuſcipimus vt cum pace &amp; ſine iniuria viuimus,</hi> To this end wee vndertake warres, that we may enioy peace without iniury: and in another place of the ſame Booke, writing to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; We muſt in matters of aduice not ſo denie warre, as to neglect our owne welfare: And one ſaith no leſſe pithily then prettily, <hi>Bellum bello ſuſceptum bellum eſt;</hi> Warres well vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, are good and lawfull, for as we muſt be cautelous not vpon euery light occaſion to vndertake it, ſo wee muſt not be cowards vpon iuſt cauſe to refuſe it, for both of them are the extreames of fortitude, as well a raſh attempt, as a baſe refuſall: From hence <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> that King of Orators, in a inuectiue Oration againſt King <hi>Philip,</hi> for his inſatiable ambitious deſire of gonernement, as he already had beſieged the Olinthians, vpon the conqueſt of whom he had a free paſſage into Athens, which to preuent, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> exhorts them not onely to aide the Olinthians, but alſo to raiſe an Army to ſend into Macedonia, that ſo being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at home, hee might haue the leſſe liberty to hurt abroad, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging that aide to their Neighbours is very requiſite, ſince as their ſafety was founded vpon their good ſucceſſe, for whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer withdraweth his helping hand, when as his neighbours houſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16363:10"/>is on fire, may want aſſiſtance to quench his owne, according to that old and vſuall verſe, <hi>I am mea res agitur paries cum proximus audet;</hi> It is my caſe: ſo when the next walles burned, either for the ſubuerſion of any tyrant, which doth wrongfully vſurpe more by might then right any others dominions: in ſo much that in former times, it was held a thing conuenient in former times, that if any Prince did tyrannically abuſe any of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, either with cruelty, murther, rape, rauine, or ſuch like op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, wherein he might offer his ſubiects opprobrious iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the which (in regard they cannot redreſſe themſelues, for what ſubiect dares lift vp his hand againſt Gods Annointed, or to ſtand vp in Armes againſt his Soueraigne) it was requiſite that the next adioyning Prince, who was a borderer vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of his Dominions, ſhould aſſume armes againſt him, to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe, correct, and reforme ſo great enormities, to the end that the name of a King might not ſeeme odious, and be hatefull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, as was <hi>Nero, Heligabulus. Dionyſius,</hi> and too many others of that barbarous diſpoſition and horrid cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>From whence he purchaſed vnto himſelfe ſuch an immortall name, and neuer dying memory, as they did diefie him for vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying ſuch monſters, and exerciſing his proweſſe vpon ſuch ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</p>
            <p>But for the better ſatisfaction of thoſe, whoſe preciſe conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, will not allow any Warres or diſſentions, to keepe any har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monicall conſent either with goodneſſe or godlineſſe, giue but an attentiue and patient eare vnto the words of <hi>Hieronymus O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorius,</hi> as they be recorded and written in his Booke entituled <hi>True Chriſtian Nobility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither hath this allowance of Wartes onely approbation from him, but is receiued as a lawfull practiſe by the common conſent of the moſt, or at leaſt the beſt part of Doctors; Diuine <hi>Plato</hi> extolleth this art of Armes, and commandeth that children ſhould be inſtructed in it, ſo ſoone as they came to ability of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, or any aptitude to diſcharge the Offices of Souldiers, and it was <hi>Cyrus</hi> his opinion, that it was as neceſſary as agriculture
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16363:10"/>or husbrandy, neither is it denyed by <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Bernards</hi> thoſe two famous Fathers.</p>
            <p>The Romanes alſo who were of matchleſſe worth in marſhall affaires, being no leſſe to be admited for their carriage abroade, then for their counſell at home, appointed for their chiefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders two Conſuls, the one to determine City affaires, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be occupied in marſhall diſcipline, being aſſured that they could neuer haue peace within their walles, except they had wartes abroade; to omit the iudgement of <hi>Hipodam us Mileſius,</hi> a man ſo expert in all learning, who thought it conuenient for that City or Countrey which coueted quietneſſe, and ſought for ſafetie, to diuide their people into three parts, the one of which were to be appointed to be Artificers, the other for Husbandry, and the third ſort ſet apart to bee imployed in martiall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.</p>
            <p>Indeede peace is a precious pearle, and is chiefly to be deſired, but oftentimes Warres muſt be performed, that peace may be maintained: euen like a ſhippe which being in her quiet Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is conſtrained to looſe Anchor, and to ſeeke for ſafety in the vaſte and raging Sea: if a man cannot attaine his right with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violence, hee may lawfully take vp Armes, and get it by force, for ſome men are like a nettle, the more kindly they vſe them, the worſe they will ſting them, the fairer they intreate them, the fouler they intertaine them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> likewiſe preſcribeth a time for peace, and a time for Warre, a day of mirth, and a day of mourning, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to vſe time when oceaſion ſerueth, is a maine pont of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall wiſedome, and to aſſume Armes vpon due premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not incenſiderately to enter into conſlict and skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, for that faucurs of ſauage beaſtlineſſe, and not of ſage humanitie: but when time permitteth, and neceſſitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, then on with your Armour, fight manfully, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an happie and honourable death, before a diſgracefull and miſerable death.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16363:11"/>
            <p>There is a double kinde of Iniuſtice, the one in offering, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuffering Iniuſtice: the one is actiuely, the other paſſiuely vniuſt, wittingly to offend againſt a neighbour, is a ſinne againſt our brother, and wilfully to beare an iniury, is an offence againſt ones ſelfe, and therefore I will not be a foe to my Neighbour, in wronging of him, neither will I bee an enemy to my ſelfe, in permitting him to offend me, when I am of ability to defend my ſelfe: But me thinkes I heare ſome obiect againſt the former reſolution, ſaying, that Truth it ſelfe hath prohibited the rendring of euill for euill to any man, and hath inioyned, that if one hath receiued a blow of one eare, hee ought to turne the other: It is true that he hath ſaid; I beleeue that vengeance is the Lords, and hee will repay it, yet notwithſtanding a Chriſtian doth not goe about to reuenge it, as it is an iniury done to himſelfe, but as an offence committed againſt God, who hath forbidden all iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and commanded to giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which belongeth vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and I truſt that no man will be ſo fooliſhly opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, that when he is oppreſſed by any Tyrant, ſhould willingly ſurrender into his hands his poſſeſſions, his Crowne, and Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory, or that it ſhould not be a legall honeſt courſe, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentane either from reaſon or religion, for a Prince to defend and maintaine his right, or that it ſhould not bee lawfull for him to warre vpon him either for it, in the defence of true Religion, or the maintenance of their freedome and liberty, as the Athenians againſt King <hi>Philip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And howſoeuer in this our Pilgrimage, fortitudes eſtimation is in the wayne, yet in ancient times proweſſe was of ſuch price and valour, of ſo great accompt, as no glory was counted ſo great, no renowne ſo honourable, as that which hath beene wonne in the field by the force of martiall proweſſe, and to make men more greedy of ſuch gain, and more thirſty of ſuch atchieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, great meedes and rich rewards were conferred vpon ſuch as had deſerued worthily, and behaued themſelues brauely in the warres.</p>
            <p>The noble <hi>Caleb,</hi> who by a conſtant courage and couragious conſtancy of minde, had reperſwaded the children of Iſrael, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16363:11"/>had a determinate inclination to make a returne into the Land of Egypt, to continue ſtill in their courage, their former manhood and vertue: and therefore the Lord promiſed to be his rewarder, who hauing a Daughter of incomparable matchleſſe beauty, whoſe name <hi>Achſat,</hi> would eſpouſe or giue her in marriage vpon none but hee that by his valour could take the City Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riath, which in the end was taken by <hi>Othniel</hi> his brothers ſonne.</p>
            <p>And did not <hi>Dauid</hi> receiue great riches with the Daughter of King <hi>Saul,</hi> for ouerthrowing <hi>Goliah?</hi> who alſo promiſed a great reward to thoſe which would worke the deſtruction of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites: The Carthaginians rewarded the Souldiers with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rings as they had beene in battels: The Scithians permitted none to drinke in a great cup of gold, that was carried about, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they had wrought the ouerthrow, or brought an Enemy to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The Romanes the more to accend mens mindes, and to ſet their breaſts on fire with the deſire of honour, and to pricke them on to proweſſe, inuented ſtately triumphs, whereby his name might mount on the wings of Fame, which had deſerued wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, but on the contrary, ſuch as had beene of cowardly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or had any affinitie with our carpet Knights, were in a moſt ſhamefull manner diſgraced.</p>
            <p>The Macedonians did conſtitute a Law, that whoſoeuer had not got the conqueſt of ſome one in fight or battaile, becauſe hee had not ſtriuen like a man for victory, he ſhould be hanged like a dogge in a halter.</p>
            <p>The Women of Cimbria beyond the valour of their See, ſlew all ſuch that being ſo followed with feare, forſooke the Field, although they were of their neuer ſo neere alliance, and were conioyned neuer ſo vnto them in the bond of conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</p>
            <p>The Women of Sparta would goe into the Field, the battaile being ended, to ſee in what places their Husbands had receiued their wounds, the which if they found them to be before, (from whence they might coniecture hee had fought manfully) they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16363:12"/>would with great ſolemnitie performe his; but if behind, they left him as being aſhamed of ſuch a coward, and would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord his carcaſſe ſo much as buriall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tierias</hi> a certain woman of <hi>Lacedemonia,</hi> hauing intelligence that her ſonne had receiued a fatall wound in the warres, and had ſhaken hands and taken his farewell of this world, replied, was it not neceſſary that my ſonne, going vnto the warres, ſhould be the death of others, then wherefore ſhould I lament if others haue beene the death of him, ſurely with leſſe ſorrow and more ſolace I remember him, ſuppoſing him no whit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of me or his predeceſſours in that he liued not in ſhame and idleneſſe, but died with honour: let cowardly hearts lament ſuch a loſſe, as for my part, I will intombe my ſonne and neuer weepe vpon his vrne.</p>
            <p>Another woman of <hi>Lacedemonia</hi> bereaued her ſonne of his vitall breath, to whom her wombe had giuen life, becauſe he had baſely fied from the warres, in whoſe reproch this epitaph was written.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Here doth the daſtard knight <hi>Damation</hi> lie,</l>
               <l>Who like a coward from the warres did ſlie:</l>
               <l>And for that fact was by his mother ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he her and Spartan blood did ſtaine.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Solon</hi> that wiſe and worthy Phyloſopher, whom wee all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, but ſcarce imitate for his wiſdome; being demaunded of <hi>Craſus</hi> the King, of who in his conceit was moſt fortunate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Tellus</hi> an Athenian from whoſe loines was ſprung (in a countrey flowing with milke and honey, and abounding with all good commodities) a great many of children, both for the indowments of the minde, and beautie of the body, abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16363:12"/>accompliſht, who defended his countrey manfully, liued with honour, died with glory.</p>
            <p>Here then you may perceiue the great eſtimation that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour was in former times when as it was ſo worthily reputed the exerciſers of it ſo much encouraged, and the neglecters of it ſo much contemned, now what incommodity hath inſued v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, who haue placed there ſole and whole ſelicity in peace that they haue not onely deſpiſed warre, but haue vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſed to learne all Marſhall diſcipline, hereafter I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate vnto you.</p>
            <p>But ſtill me thinkes there remaines a ribble rabble of ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming religious people, whoſe queaſie conſciences ſtrayne at a Gnat, but ſwallow a Camell, whoſe warie minds ſtumble at a ſtraw, but leap ouer a block, which ſtill doe oppoſe and make aſſault againſt our poſition, in regard that murther ſpoyles, and ſundry other inconueniences are the effects of them: but it is not inough to reproue an opinion as erronious, except they proue it falſe, neither doth this there meere aſſertion ſufficient to infringe the verity of this poſition. Suppoſe Warre to be the mother of Murther, yet it is oftentimes ſuch as is by God allowed, nay more commaunded: Did not <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> fearing the day would haue impoſed too ſpeedy and preſent a period to his ſlaughter, commaund the Sunne to ſtay in <hi>Gideon,</hi> and the Moone in the <hi>Aialon,</hi> and the Lord did countenance his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, for there ſuccecded an immediate Solſtyne, and the Moone continued not her courſe, nay oftentimes the too much fauouring of ours and Gods enemies, hath beene the onely meanes to roote vs out of Gods fauour: For what was the originall of <hi>Sauls</hi> deſtruction? but the not deſtroying of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> neither doe I produce theſe examples, to proue warres alwayes neceſſary: but ſometimes lawfull, and I can not chooſe but admire the fooliſh frenſie of ſome fantaſtique Coxcombes, who doe ſo much miſconceiue of warres as they hold them directly diſpleaſing to God, becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16363:13"/>murther, and diuers other miſdemeanors are committed in them.</p>
            <p>But by theſe arguments they kill themſelues with their owne weapons, and ſeeking to maintaine the prerogatiue of peace, doe quite cuert it, for by that argument it is the moſt to bee euited en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormity that can be imagined: for is it not the nurſe of vices, the roote of ruine, the prop of pride, to be ſhort, the mother of all miſchiefe: for in the time of peace wee fixe our fancie onely vpon vncertaine riches, for the ſatisfying of which ſacred hunger of gold, what offence will wee not perpetrate, what ſinne will wee leaue vnacted, who will not become an Vſurer, or an Extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nay, that which is ſomething better, a hangman, or an Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner, a paraſite, nay, a paracide, to purchaſe them? And when they haue attained them, they are but the <hi>irratamenta malorum,</hi> the ingines of iniquitie, the inſtruments of vanitie, the ſtirrers vp of ſtrife and contention, making the poſſeſſor of them proude, preſumptuous, vain-glorious, and like leauen ſowring the whole lumpe. This <hi>Auguſtine</hi> perceiuing, writeth in a Booke of his entituled <hi>De Ciuitate Dei,</hi> The City of Carthage was more hurtfull to the Citie of Rome after her deſtruction, then in the time of the warres which the Romanes had with her, for whileſt they had enemies in Affticke, they knew not what vices meant at Rome.</p>
            <p>Yet is it not my drift to preferre Warres before Peace, but to intimate, that as Peace is the great bleſſing of God, ſo Warres vndertaken vpon due conſideration, doe nothing offend him: and although in the time of peace there is plentie of vice, yet notwithſtanding it is not abſolutely to be condemned, ſo though in the Warres there be many outrages committed, yet it is not wholly therefore to be neglected: the Sunne ſhining vpon ſome pleaſant Garden, makes the flowres haue a more fragrant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull ſmell, but diſplaying his moſt radiant beames vpon a dunghill, maketh the ſtinke greater, and the ſent more noy ſome: The ſicke mans ſtomacke turneth all his meate into bad humors, Peace may be proſperous, and Warre lawfull, yet both of them may be abuſed.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16363:13"/>
            <p>Moreouer, if I ſhould ſpeake of the particular commodities that ſeuerall countries haue reaped by warres, I could be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and to the intent I may not range farre abrode for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, let thy conſideration make but a ſtep into our neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nations, and let vs looke into the Low Countries, theſe you ſhall ſee the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that treaſury of all vertue and goodneſſe, though with meane forces, withſtanding a mighty nation, that his libertie might not be infringed, of his country iniured; neither hath he maintained his owne caſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly valiantly, but hath afforded his neighbouring friends aide and aſſiſtance. Let Spaine ſpeake how often ſhe hath receiued a repulſe and <hi>a non viſitauit</hi> from him? how often in vaine ſhee hath attempted his ouerthrow, but be like a well built fort hath valiantly withſtood all their aſſaults? and though he hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily beene moued, yet could not be remoued by their attempts: whereby as all men ſufficiently vnderſtand, hee is now growne potent and powerfull, rich and renowned: whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if Aſſe-like he would haue borne the king of Spaines heauy burthen, ſubmitted to the yoke of his obedience, he had loſt his libertie, nouer attained the honor with which his name is now crowned, for he remaineth as a mirrour and terrour to all nations, for as his Excellency did iuſtly, and with due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration vndertake, ſo hee hath nobly and with true valour maintained his quarrell againſt the King of Spaine. Surely an act well beſeeming ſo worthy and noble a Prince, who as hee ſhould not be like a raw wound ouer-apprehenſiue of iniuries, ſo he ſhould be vnlike dead fleſh, not too ſenſleſſe of wrongs done vnto: the one ſhewes folly the other fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. Neither would it ill befeeme any Potentate to treade in the ſteps of ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Prince, and not ſo much to reſpect peace as to neglect a iuſt occaſion of warre, for doth it ſtand with reaſon or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that a Prince hauing ſufficient power to make reſiſtance to an open enemy, ſhould expoſe his open breſt to his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſword, nay when he ſees he hath already cut off ſome of his lims to truſt him with his whole body. Hath he any great good meaning to the tree that hackes and hewes downe the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16363:14"/>branches: doth he beare any good affection to the father that ſtriueth to iniure the child? or doth not he that oppreſſeth the child, expreſſe his hatred to the father? can one which loathes the effect loue the cauſe? will not hee which cannot tollerate the heate, labour to quench the fire? yes ſurely, and it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly lawfull for Kings to ſeeke to depoſe a Tyrant though he had no intereſt in thoſe which were iniured. Then how much more forcible a motiue hath hee if his poſteritie bee abuſed, and he be wounded in his owne bowels: Surely his ſword ought not to reſt in his ſheath when he hath ſuch iuſt cauſe to draw it, but his angry canons to thunder in the eares of his enemies, and tell them they haue iniured him. And is not this the cauſe of our Soueraigne, if euer Prince had iuſt cauſe of warre, it is he, for they haue exiled out of his inheritance the <hi>Palſgraue,</hi> a Prince ſo hopefull; they haue layd waſt his countrey which was the Paradiſe of the world, a land ſo fruitfull, they doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly vſurpe his Diadem, they haue falſely promiſed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of it, when as the pulſes of their promiſes did not beat according to the motion of their hearts. Certes it did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme Princely pietie in them to offer, neither doth it conſent with kingly courage in him to ſuffer, that me thinkes this voyce of the Souldier is but as an echo to the voyce of heauen, which ſayes the cauſe is iuſt, and counſelleth all Chriſtan Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes ioyntly to aſſume armes to driue this Boare out of the Vineyard, and to re-ſeate this royall Prince in his Throne and dignitie.</p>
            <p>Heare oh you braue Engliſh Spirits which once were admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I had almoſt ſayd adored for your valour when you had imployment; how can you any longer deſiſt from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of honour in ſo iuſt a cauſe? doe you not long to fight for the ſafetie of a limme, nay the halfe part of your Soueraigne. But why ſhould I vſe theſe needleſſe perſwaſions, or ſpurre a free horſe, I dare ſay you are eaſily intreated, nay hardly perſwaded from it, and you are as reſtleſſe being ſtaued from the combat, as the Stone violently detained from the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16363:14"/>
            <p>Neuer was Beare robbed of her whelpes more angrie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge then you of this enterpriſe; it may be indeed there bee ſome Spaniſh Engliſh (as they terme them) who are neither true to God, their King, or countrey, which haue not the leaſt drop of loyall blood lodged in their hearts, that would be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vnwilling to act a part in this matter: perhaps likewiſe there be others who be guilty of ſo little valour, that they had rather liue like drones in this hiue of our commonwealth, and be loitring lubbers at home, then any waies to offer there ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice for their Soueraignes welfare, or ſpend a dram, nay a drop of blood in the defence of the truth, who are very well content to enioy the warmth they haue vnder the wings of their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, but will not do any ſeruice in the requital of this benefit being not much vnlike to vngratefull curs which will fawne vpon their maſter ſo long as he feeds them, but when hee hath any futther imployments for them, they bid him adue, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to their kennels: So theſe men, or rather beaſts indeeed, that are borne, bred, foſtered, ſed, in their countrey, and yet can ſuffer an indignitie done to their Prince, and when their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſtandeth in need of their aid or aſſiſtance, to ſlip their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler &amp; come to combat in the defence of it as willingly as Bears to the ſtake: that argueth an vngratefull mind, free from all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as well as vallour, and indeed are no more worthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the commodities and benefits of their countrey then a Swine deſerues a pearle.</p>
            <p>But as <hi>Plutarque</hi> maketh mention of an Iland in Greece cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cobde,</hi> in which there was a linage deſcended from that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble valiant captaiue called <hi>Agis</hi> the good, amongſt which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitas</hi> this law eſpecially was moſt ſtrictly obſerued, that none durſt preſume to ſtile himſelfe naturally borne in the Ile, vnleſſe he had performed ſome memorable valiant act: or at the leaſt, ſhewed himſelfe forward and willing in the defence of his King and Countrie, and I dare truely ſay, though he dare ſtyle himſelfe one of the Countrie naturally borne, yet he is not ſo, for a true Engliſh man hath a heart more full of Celeſtiall fire, and a boſome better furniſht with noble thoughts, then to be a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16363:15"/>Porter of iniuries done to his Soueraigne, or any of thoſe which belong vnto him: And I do ſpeake, <hi>ex animo,</hi> there neuer went a hungry man with a greater or better appetyte to a feaſt, then they would to this fray. They know the Prince ſo worchy, the cauſe ſo iuſt, the ſucceſſe ſo certaine: I doubt not, but it hath bin ſo ſufficiently proued, that warres are lawfull, that a blind man may apparantly ſee it: but ſtill there are ſome, who though they can not diſallow of the action, yet they ſeeme to diſlike of the Agents, and perhaps they will ſay, a Soldiour can not be an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, becauſe in warres they be miniſters of ſo much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe: this is their reaſon. But in this place I will but reaſon of ſouldiours, as I haue already done or warres: that is, but to ſhew what maner of people ſouldiours haue beene: As for ſuch as doe but vſurpe the name of ſouldiours, I leaue them tyll ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion.</p>
            <p>We finde in the 14 Chapter of the booke of Geneſis,
<note place="margin">Geneſis. 14.</note> that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was a captaine and leader of men, vnto whom <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedech</hi> the King of <hi>Salem</hi> brought foorth bread and wyne: albeit he wore a Prieſt of the moſt high God. And S. <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Hebrues the 6. Chapter, ſpeaking of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>That he was made a high Frieſt for euer after the order of Melch zedech:</hi> and all the Diuine &amp; ancient Doctors by generall conſent do agree, that the firſt true figure of Chriſt, was here offered to ſouldiers, that were returned from the flaughter and ſpoyle of their enemies.</p>
            <p>A ſpeciall cauſe wherein ſouldiers may worthily triumph, &amp; a choake peare ſufficient, to ſtop their mouthes, that would ſo abſolutely condemne them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 18.21. Deut. 1.13.15.</note> though he were otherwiſe a Prophet, yet he was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife a captaine, to whom <hi>Jethro</hi> his father in law, by the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods ſpirit, gaue counſell to prouide ſuch to be iudges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the reſt, which ſhould be found to bee men of courage, to feare God, to be louers of trueth, and hating couetouſneſſe, &amp;c. and that of them he ſhould make ſome <hi>Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enaries</hi> to rule ouer thouſands; and that he ſhould cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te others <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nteniers,</hi> to rule ouer hundreds: other <hi>Conquest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iers</hi> to beare authority ouer fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16363:15"/>and <hi>Diſniers</hi> to commaund our tennes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſua,</hi> at whoſe commandement the ſonne was obedient,
<note place="margin">Iudges. 7.</note> was a ſouldier and a leader of an armie.</p>
            <p>When the whole hoſt of the children of Iſrael was vtterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide for the multitude of their enemies, whoſe number was like the ſandes of the ſea, the Lord commanded <hi>Gedeon</hi> to make his choyſe of ſuch to ſerue for ſouldiers to encounter them, as were moſt faythfull, that doubted not of his promiſes made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, which were in number but 300. and were choſen by lapping of water.</p>
            <p>Who euer ſtood more in the good grace and fauour of God, then that noble King and captaine <hi>Dauid,</hi> whom the Lord ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be a man after his owne hart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire?</p>
            <p>What ſhould I here ſpeake of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heth,</hi> of <hi>Jehu,</hi> of <hi>Judas Macchabaeus,</hi> and of many other, which were notable ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? ſhall they be condemned to be wicked and euill, becauſe they were warriours? or ſhall we thinke of them, that in that vocation they offended God?</p>
            <p>When the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uldiers demaunded of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 3.</note> what they ought to doe, he willed them to hurt no man wrongfully, but to liue by their wages: he ſayd not vnto them, Forſake your vyle profeſſion, you can not be the children of God, to follow any ſuch manner of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>cyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: the which queſtionleſſe he would haue done, if he had ſo thought.</p>
            <p>And when the Captaine, who had ſent vnto leſus for the healing of his ſeruant that lay ſick, as Ieſus was going towards his houſe:
<note place="margin">Luke. 7.</note> (<hi>Nay Lord</hi> quoth the Captaine) <hi>I am not worthy that thou ſhouldeſt enter into my rooſe, doe but ſpeake the word onely, and my ſeruant ſhall be ſafe: for I alſo am a man ſet vnder power, and haue vnder me ſouldiers: and I ſay vnto one go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and he goeth: and to another come, and he commeth: and to myſeruant doe this, and he doth it.</hi> Ieſus maruelling at his words, turning him about to thoſe that followed, ſayd: <hi>I haue not found ſo great faith, no not in Jſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what godlyer commendation may be giuen to any man then we finde in the 10. Chapter of the Actes of the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Actes. 10.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16363:16"/>where it is written as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was a certaine man in Caeſarea, whoſe name was Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius, a captaine of the ſouldiers of Italy, a deuout man, and one that feared God with all his houſhold, &amp;c.</hi> To this <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Angell of the Lord appeared, and willed him to ſend into <hi>Joppa,</hi> and to inquire for one <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> who ſhould inſtruct him and baptiſe him in the name of Ieſus, and when the Angell was departed, thus ſayth the text: <hi>He called to him two of his houſhold ſeruants, and a deuout ſouldier, that wayted on him, &amp; told them all the matter, and ſent them to Ioppa, &amp;c.</hi> This may ſeeme ſufficient to proue, that not onely Captaynes, but alſo priuate ſouldiers, haue beene found to be both zealous and feruent in the loue and feare of God, and that he hath likewyſe accepted them into his ſpeciall grace and fauour.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould I ſtand here to manifeſt the vertues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a number of noble captaines haue beene moſt plenteouſly indued: as the bountie and liberality of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie of <hi>Scipio;</hi> the iuſtice and equity of <hi>Iultus Caeſar,</hi> the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and humility of <hi>Agathocles,</hi> the mercy and pitie of <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus,</hi> the faith and fidelity of <hi>Regulus</hi> to his very enemies. Here might (I ſay) euen of this onely matter a huge volume be written, onely of the vertuous diſpoſitions of noble ſouldiers: in ſo much that this oath, <hi>By the faith of a Souldier,</hi> hath beene ſo inuiolably kept, that a ſouldier hath beene better to haue beene credited by that oath, then ſome merchants now by their obligations.</p>
            <p>But here if any will coniecture, that in tyme paſt ſouldiers haue ſo exceeded in vertues, that at the time preſent they haue none at all leſt for them to boaſt on: although in <hi>England</hi> our multitude be not many, yet amongſt thoſe few there bee both honourable and worſhipfull, whoſe magnanimity in the tyme of warres hath made them famous in forreine countries, and whoſe noblenes and vertues now in the time of peace, do ſhine coequall with the beſt.</p>
            <p>But here peraduenture ſome curious caueller will replie, that theſe may be better called ſage and wyſe counſellers, then
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16363:16"/>bloodie or cruell Captaines: and rather may bee termed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and diſcreet luſtices, then raſh and harbrayned ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and thus by denying them to be ſouldiers, will thinke I am neuer the neerer my proofe. But here if there were no other ſhift, or that the matter were ſo needefull to bee reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on: it were very eaſie to proue, that the beſt and nobleſt ſouldiers bee euer found to be the wyſeſt and meeteſt Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: and for that cauſe the Poets haue fayned <hi>Minerua</hi> to be armed, ſignifying that Captaines and ſouldiers ſhould bee (as it is reported of <hi>Iugerth</hi>) not onely wyſe in counſelling, but couragious in conquering: as politick in keeping, as valiant in getting.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Tullie</hi> in his firſt booke of <hi>Offices</hi> ſpeaketh of a double commodity that theſe men do yeeld to their countrie,
<note place="margin">Tull. de oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, lib. 1.</note> who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, do make warres: &amp; roabed, do gouerne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth.</p>
            <p>What though there be ſome that in the tyme of ſeruice, will intrude themſelues, and become ſouldiers, of purpoſe rather to ſpoyle, robbe, and filch, then to do any good ſeruice, ſhall the honeſt Souldier therefore be condemned? ſo euery profeſſion, how neceſſary ſo euer it ſeeme, would be miſliked, and men of euery faculty would be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>As firſt for example, the Merchants, whoſe trade, as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſayth, was inuented for the neceſſity of mans life, tranſporting from one region to another, that which lacketh in the one and aboundeth in the other: yet there bee many that vnder this cloake and good pretence, continually do pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, to tranſport out of their owne natiue countries, ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities as may not well be ſpared: whereby many times great ſcarcity and dearth doth happen, wherein the people are piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>In <hi>England</hi> once a yeare we finde the extremity, either for want of corn, leather, hides, tallow, butter, cheeſe, bacon, beefe, beere, and many other ſuch like, which by his Maieſtie are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited: but no reſtraint may ſerue againſt thoſe theeues, vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall robbers and ſpoylers of theis owne countrie.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe are commonly the greateſt find-faults that will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16363:17"/>inuey againſt ſouldiers, whoſe ſpoyles are much more tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe they ſpoyle but their enemies: theſe rob and ſpoile their friends, and make wracke of their owne countries, by conueying away their commodities, and by returning of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities, vaine trifles, which are not neceſſary for humane life, but onely to maintaine women and children in pride, pompe and vaineglory, ſuch things as do procure delights, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and delicacie: the very vanities and vices of euery nation by theſe men are brought home. And then what p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, what fraude what deceit by themſelues, their brokers, and retailers is vſed to vtter them, my wits be too weake, nor I thinke there is no other that is able to expreſſe, vnleſſe it bee a Merchant himſelfe that hath vſed the trade.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, vnder this trade and trafficke, they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with ſtrange Princes, and vtter vnto them the ſecrets of countries, lend them mony, and in the end will not ſticke to betray their owne countrie and commonwealth.</p>
            <p>There is another kinde of Merchants, that decke their ſhops with other mens goods, borrowing here of one, and there of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: and when they haue gotten into their hands ſome great maſſe or value, then they become bankrupts, and liue in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with other mens goods.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee, that although this trade or trafficke of merchandize is very beneficiall to euery ſtate and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and that there haue beene many wiſe and notable men thet haue vſed it, as <hi>Thaluſt, Solon, Hippocrates,</hi> and others, yet it is by ſome abuſed: but ſhall wee therefore condemne the trade, or other good and honeſt merchants that vſe it? not ſo, for the exerciſe of it may not be forborne, and the honeſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Merchant is to be had in reuerence and eſtimation.</p>
            <p>In like manner amongſt the Lawyers, are there not found many that creepe in to the Innes of Court, that ſeeke by law to ouer throw law, ſuch as be termed by the name of <hi>Peti foggers,</hi> brethels, that practiſe nothing but to breede diſſentions, ſtrifes ſuits, quarrels, and debates betweene neighbour and neighbor brother and brother, yea ſomtimes between the father and the ſonne?</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16363:17"/>
            <p>Firſt they animate them to commence actions, perſwading them that their quarrels be iuſt, and will very well ſtand with law: but when they haue once gotten them in, then they feed them with delayes, procraſtinating their ſuits from day to day, from terme to terme, yea from yeere to yeere: in the end, when the matter is like to fall out againſt them, then they blame their clients, that in the beginning they did not throughly inſtruct them.</p>
            <p>Theſe be people that of all other are moſt to be deteſted: for in the time of peace, theſe procure continuall warres, and ciuill diſſentions, not amongſt enemie, but amongſt friends, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt forraine foes, but amongſt their naturall country men, reioycing when any bral or brabble doth fall out amongſt their neighbours.</p>
            <p>And yet they would be accounted the authours of peace, &amp; will not let to exclaime againſt the ſouldiour, and condemne him, becauſe they doe thinke him to be like vnto themſelues, that is, to be deſirous of warres and troubles.</p>
            <p>There is no Parliament or conuocation that is called, but if there be any good motion had in queſtion, for the quietneſſe or quicke diſpatch of matters in controuerſie, but that lawyers be the only lets that it ſhall not come forth: becauſe that if it were not for delaies and ſhifts, the one halfe, nay not a quarter of them might be able to thriue by their occupation, there are ſuch a ſhamefull company.</p>
            <p>Yea, many times there are found great coriuptions euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Iudges themſelues: that for feare to offend a Prince or ſome Noble man, will not ſticke with Pilate to condemne Chriſt. Sometime with Gold and Siluer or other gifts, they be ſo corrupted, that they regard more the preſents that are giuen them, then either iuſtice or equitie: they are diligent in rich mens cauſes, put the poore they deſerre: the complaint of the widow or fatherleſſe cannot be heard amongſt them.</p>
            <p>But ſhall we therefore reproue the law, which is the onely prop and ſtay to euery commonwealth, without the which we could not liue in any good order, otherwiſe then as brute beaſts neither could thoſe that be good and harmleſſe, enioy either
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16363:18"/>goods or poſſeſſions from cruell Firants and oppreſſours? nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were any one man aſſared of his life or liuing, were there not law to puniſh murtherers, and to maintaine right: or ſhall the abuſes of ſome, condemne all honeſt and true dealing law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, who in their profeſſion of all men are worthy to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? As there is no reaſon in the one, ſo they be too much to blame, that for the lewdneſſe of ſome loſſes, that doe but vſurp the name names of ſouldiers, will therefore ſo abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all ſouldiers, thinking there can be no good, becauſe ſome are ill. But what profeſſion may there be, wherein wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men will not ſeeke to cloke and couer themſelues? Be there not that enter euen into the Miniſtery of the holy ſacraments, prowd prelates, blinde guides, and lazie lubbers: ſome that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpace of twentie yeeres, haue receiued the fruits of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, that haue not three times viſited their ſlocke, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits them to Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> lacke latine and his fellow, poore igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Chaplaines: ſuch as they hire beſt cheape: while they themſelues liue in pleaſure, pompe and pride: not like <hi>S. Peter</hi> nor S. <hi>John,</hi> that had not one peny to giue to the poore lame man, that ſat begging at the temple gate: and yet they would be called their ſucceſſors? Theſe be they of whom the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel</hi> ſo exclaimeth, ſaying, They ſerue for nothing, but to ſerue themſelues, and in ſteed of feeding their flocke, they take the fleece, draw the milke, kill the fatteſt, eate the fleſh, breake the bones: they are dumbe dogges, that know nothing, they dare not barke, but are very curious to haue horſekeepers for their Palfries, Falkconers for their Hawkes, Cookes for their Panches, but the poore ſheepe periſh through their default. I know likewiſe that there be a number of a learned Paſtors, godly miniſters, diligent Preachers, and faithfull followers: they which (God defend) ſhould beare the abuſes of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Then if the holy temple of God, cannot be cleanſed from ſuch Miniſters of miſchiefes: they be ſomething too nice, that would haue ſouldiers to be all Saints, and much more to blame that would make them all diuels: becauſe ſome doe amiſſe. And here withall I muſt thinke them to be very partiall, that with ſuch blunts termes will intitle
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16363:18"/>Souldiers in the time of Warre: and in the time of peace, can ſo cleanly cloake the very ſame Actors, with names and titles of credite and eſtimation. For in the time of Warres, he that is found to be bloudily minded, killing without compaſſion all that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his wrath, they terme him by the name of a Tyrant and a murtherer, where in the time of peace, they ſometime ſhadow him vnder the title of my Lord Iudge, but many times by the name of Maſter luſtice of Peace and Quorum. In the time of Warre, whom they terme a ſeditious mutiner, a peruerter of good Lawes, a maintainer of vngodly quarrels: In the time of Peace they call him Maſter Sergiant of the Quoife, a wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor in the Law, or an honeſt viligent Atturney. In the time of Warre, whom they terme a thiefe, a robber, a ſpoiler. In the time of peace they call him an honeſt trading Merchant. In the time of Warrie whom they call a violator of Women, a rauiſher, and deflowrer: In the time of peace they call him a friendly and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gentleman: yea, and ſome fooliſh ſoother, that will ſpeake they know not what, will ſay he is a right Courtier, and a Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like gentleman. In the time of Warre, he that can tell a filed tale, and that can creepe into mens boſomes to ſerue his owne turne, they call him a Paraſite, a flatterer, and a diſſembler: In the time of peace they call him an excellent learned man, and a verie good Preacher.</p>
            <p>Such partialitie (I ſay) is amongſt them, that no faults are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied, but ſuch as be committed amongſt Souldiers: Neither doe I here goe about to excuſe all Souldiers, as though there were none ill: but thoſe that be, are commonly found in theſe new leuied bands, &amp; not a mongſt old ſouldiers, as hereafter I wil ſhew.</p>
            <p>But here (peraduenture) ſome will thinke, that although many of them may be excuſed from a number of vices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue beene charged: yet that they of force muſt be all murtherers, may not be denied: for they goe into the Field as well weaponed to kill, as armed to defend. This obiection I haue many times heard, but thoſe people are in too ſcrupulous an opinion, conſidering how many examples wee may finde in the holy Bible: where God hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16363:19"/>not beene offended, with thoſe that haue killed their enemies: but that is ſometimes lawfull in the preſence of God to ſhake off the yoke of bondage by the death of Tirants, as <hi>Judith</hi> by <hi>Holofernes,</hi> and many other like. But as iuſtice without tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is reputed iniurie: ſo magnanimitie without mercie is accounted Tiranny: and as it cannot be counted a noble vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie which bringeth not with it ſome clemencie, ſo to vſe pittie out of time and ſeaſon is as great folly, as to vſe mercy in any conflict till victorie attained.</p>
            <p>And ſometimes policie excludeth pittie, as the Greeks, who after the deſtruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> ſlew <hi>Aſtinax</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hector,</hi> to the end that there might remaine no occaſion of quarrell, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring if he had liued, he would haue ſought ſome reuenge.</p>
            <p>Indeed they may ſay ſouldiers are moſt mercileſſe, but there are ſundry moſt miſerable. Firſt, in the time of warres, they ſpare not in their countries behalfe, to forſake their wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, father, mother, brother, ſiſter, to leaue their friends, and onely betake them againſt their enemies, contented to yeeld themſelues to continuall watch, ward, faſting, hunger, thirſt, cold, heate, trauell, toyle, ouer hils, woods, deſerts, wading through riuers, where many ſometimes loſe their liues by the way, lying in the field in raine, wind, froſt and ſnow, aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the enemy, the lacke of limmes, the loſſe of life, making their bodies a fence and bulwarke againſt the ſhot of the canon.</p>
            <p>But the warres being once finiſhed, and that there is no need of them, how be they rewarded, how be they cheriſhed, what account is there made of them, what other thing gaine they then ſlander, miſreport, falſe impoſitions, hatred and deſpight.</p>
            <p>How ſmall is the number that bee in England of ſufficient men, ſuch I meane as be able in deed, in the time of ſeruice, to ſtand their countrie in ſtead, to any purpoſe, and yet how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of this ſmall number haue euer beene brought to credit, or beene any thing preferred, for the ſeruice they haue done?</p>
            <p>And O England, would to God ſo many preſidents of others miſhaps might make thee take heed, &amp; call thy ſelfe to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16363:19"/>conſider thy enemies be not ſo ſecret, but they be as malicious, and haue ſtaide all this whyle neither for want of quarrell, neither for want of will, if they themſelues were once at quiet: nor flatter not thy ſelfe becauſe thou haſt enioyed a peaceable time, that it ſhall ſtill indure, but remember the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it hath beene calme, the ſooner the ſtorme is looked for, and the greater the rage when it falleth.</p>
            <p>If thou doeſt well looke into thy ſelfe, and ponder thine owne caſe, thou ſhalt ſinde, that if any ſodaine alarum ſhould happen, thy greateſt want ſhalbe onely of thoſe men that now thou holdeſt in ſo ſmall eſtimation, and doeſt eſteeme of ſo litle accompt.</p>
            <p>If thou thinkeſt thy great numbers of vntrayned men, are ſufficient to defend thee, doe but remember what happened to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> where they wanted neither men, nor any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for the warres. But they wanted ſouldiours to direct them, and men of vnderſtanding to encourage them: For the want of knowledge breedeth the want of courage, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, <hi>A wyſe man is euer ſtrong:
<note place="margin">Prou. 14.</note> yea a man of vnderstanding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth with ſtrength: for with wiſedome muſt warre be taken in hand, and where there are many that can giue counſell, there is the victorie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Xerxes,</hi> who with a great armie, was put to the worſt but with 300 <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> confeſſed that he forced not ſo much for the multitude, as for their knowledge and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I could here rehearſe many other examples of like effect, but I leaue them till other occaſion, &amp; will conclude with what care and prouiſion ſundrie noble Princes haue prouided for their ſouldiouts, not onely in the time of warre when they haue had need of them: but aſwell in the time of peace for their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice already done, that they ſhould not want, according to the minde of <hi>Alexander Seuerus,</hi> who ſayth, <hi>The ſouldiour is worthy his keeping in the time of peace, that hath honeſtly ſerued his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in the time of warre, although for age he can not trauell, yet his counſell may non be ſpared.</hi> And Ieſus the ſonne of Sirach ſayth, <hi>There bee two things that greeue my heart, and in the third is a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16363:20"/>diſpleaſure come vpon me, when an expert man of warre ſuffreth ſcarcenes and pouertie, when men of vnderſtanding and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are not ſet by, and when one departes from righteouſneſſe to ſiune, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octauian Auguſtus</hi> honored ſouldiours with this law: Whatſoeuer thou be that ſhalt ſerue with vs in warres ten yeeres ſpace, ſo that thou ſhalt be forty yeeres old, whether thou haſt ſerued on foot or on horſe-back, hereafter be thou free from warres, be thou <hi>Heros,</hi> an old ſouldier: let no man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid thee the citie, the ſtreete, the temple, nor his houſe: let no man lay any blame to thy charge, put any burden vpon thee, or aske thee any money: if thou ſhalt offend in any thing, looke to be chaſtiſed by <hi>Caeſar</hi> and by no man elſe. In all diſhonefty that men ſhall commit, I will that thou be the Iudge, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſer, whether they be priuate or officers: that which thou ſhalt ſay and affirme for trueth, no man ſhall reproue for falſe. I will that all wayes and places be open for thee, thou ſhalt haue authority to eate and drinke at princes tables: thou ſhalt yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue wages of the common treaſurie to finde thee and thy houſhold: let her be preferred before other women, whom thou ſhalt take to be thy lawfull wife: and he that thou ſhalt call in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous, let him be wicked and infamous: thou being <hi>Heros,</hi> ſhalt haue authority to beare armes, badges, names, and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which be decent for a king: doe what thou liſt in euery place and country where thou commeſt, if any do thee wrong let his head be cut off. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the great, when he had tranſlated the name of the Empire to the <hi>Gormanes,</hi> after the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Lombards</hi> were vanquiſhed, gaue this honor to his ſouldiers, ſaying: You ſhall be called <hi>Heroes,</hi> the companions of Kings, and Iudges of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences: liue ye hereafter voide of labour, counſell Kings in the publike authority, reproue diſhoneſt things, fauour women, help Orphanes, let not Princes lack your counſell, and aske of them meate, drinke and money, if any ſhall deny it, let him be unrenowmed &amp; infamous: if any doe you iniury, let him know he hath offended the Emperors Maieſty: but ye ſhall foreſee,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16363:20"/>that ye diſtaine not ſo great an honour, and ſo great a priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, gotten by the great labour of warre, with drunkenneſſe, rayling, or any other vice: to the end, that that which we haue giuen you for glory, redound not to puniſhment, which we will for euer reſerue to be giuen you by vs and our ſucceſſors, Emperors of Rome, as often as you ſhall tranſgreſſe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Polycrates</hi> of <hi>Samos,</hi> appointed liuing for the wiues and children of the dead ſouldiers, ſtreightly commaunding, that no man ſhould offend them, or do them any wrong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solon</hi> made this law, that thoſe children, whoſe fathers had ſpent their liues in fighting in the defence of the common wealth, ſhould be brought vp at the charges of the common treaſure.</p>
            <p>But what doe I ſtand reciting of ſtrange hiſtories, forepaſſed ſo many yeeres ſithence: Why do I not remember the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Spaniards, amongſt whom at this inſtant men of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice be not a little honoured, and had in eſtimation: And goe to the drunken countries of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Swethen,</hi> and thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partes of the Eaſt, and how be ſouldiers cheriſhed, &amp; men of ſeruice prouided for.</p>
            <p>Here might be many other things ſaid in the behalfe of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, the which I omit, and leauing them to the benefit of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fortune, will come to ſpeake of the abuſe of the time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16363:21"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART SHEWING THE time, when warres ought <hi>to be put in execution.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owſoeuer I know ſome will condemne my diſcourſe as friuolous and fruiteleſſe: Fot howſoeuer in other nations there hath bene a greater effuſion of the blood of men, then of Beaſts, yet we haue ſecurely ſlept vpon our Couches of eaſe, and furfeited of eaſe and plentie, yet though it be the part of a foole at the ſea, to wiſh for a ſtorme, when the weather is calme: ſo I know likewiſe in the time of calme, to prouide for a ſtorme, is the point of a wiſe mariner: for who conſidereth not, to whatdiſpoſition Kings and Princes be commonly incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, in theſe latter dayes: which is, to haue greater felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with Tyranny to offend others, then with iuſtice and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to keepe their owne: it ought therefore with great diligence to be prouided for, that like as in the time of warre, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect care of peace may not be omitted: ſo in the time of peace, ſuch things may be foreſeene, appertayning to the warre, that the want of warlike prouiſions, be not preiudiciall to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of this ſweet and quiet peace.</p>
            <p>And the very occaſion that vrgeth me to wryte, is to wiſh that in <hi>England</hi> we were expert warriers, though not warre lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: and that we had many that were wiſe, rather then willing ſouldiers. But where peace is ſo immediatly deſired, that in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring thereof they forget all Martiall exerciſes, which is the very preſeruer, &amp; maintainer of peace, (according to the minde
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16363:21"/>of <hi>Valerius Maximus,</hi> who ſayth, <hi>That the custodie of bleſsed peace conſiſteth in the knowledge of warre</hi>) it can not be choſen therefore, but thoſe people be euer neereſt their owne harme, that will ſo careleſly ſpend the time of peace, as though they ſhould neuer more haue occaſion to enter into warre,</p>
            <p>And generally it is ſeene, where pleaſure is preferred ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuely, and the people follow it ſo inordinately, that they lie and wallow in it ſo careleſly, they commonly end with it moſt miſerably.</p>
            <p>For how many Cities, how many Countries, which ſometime moſt of all floriſhed, onely by reaſon of their farre ſtretched Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, glory and renowme, purchaſed by famous and noble actes, are now beaten flat to the ground, couered with mould, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt out of remembrance.</p>
            <p>Where are now become the dominions of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Perſians?</hi> What is become of the glory of the rich citie <hi>Athens:</hi> which had bene ſo often forewarned by that excellent Orator <hi>Demoſthenes?</hi> Or where is now the pomp and power of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s?</hi> Or what hath waſted the fame and renowme of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Rome,</hi> that it had not bene perpetnall.</p>
            <p>What other thing then this inordinate delicacie, ryot and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe: For when they ouer neglected the ſeates of warre, layd aſide their weapons, ſought more for their owne priuate aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement, then for the liberties of their Countrie: then came their kingdomes to calamity, &amp; began headlong to fall to the ground: and then in the ſtead of frugality ſprung vp outragious ryot: in ſtead of hardineſſe and courage in the warres, exceeding tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and niceneſſe, both of body and minde: and thus when the knowlege of Souldierfare was extinguiſhed: then vnſatiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of riches made entrie amongſt them, and nothing ſo much practiſed, as to haue experience in buying and ſelling, that in the ende, the Emperiall Crowne was bought and ſold for money amongſt them: and the Romane Empyre which ſo mightily had floriſhed: was now made ſubiect to common thraldome.</p>
            <p>But for that there are ſome, that are nothing moued with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16363:22"/>reading of hiſtories, monuments, or the examples of auncient wryters, vnleſſe they haue knowne the like in their age, or ſeene with their eyes, or as it were touched with their ſinger, I will therefore put ſuch in remembrance of the ſtate and condition of <hi>Holland, Zeland, Flanders, Brabant,</hi> and other partes of the low cuntries: How many yeers continued they in peace &amp; quietneſſe: in drunkenneſſe, in lechery, in ryot, in exceſſe, in gluttony, in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe? (I will not ſay in the like predicament that we now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in England) the which to continue, they were contented to ſubmit themſelues to any manner of thraldome, and to euery kinde of ſlauery, to receiue the Spaniards into their cities and townes, which were naturally ſeated ſo ſtrong, that no forreine Prince could forceably haue made entrie into them.</p>
            <p>How the Spaniards gouerned them, with what rigour they ruled them, and how tyrannouſly they raigned ouer them, is ſo well knowne, as I will not ſpend the time to relate: in the end, to disburden themſelues from that which before they had yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto, by neceſſity they were inforced to goe to <hi>Mars</hi> his ſchoole, and to practiſe the art of warre, which had euer bin moſt loathſome vnto them, not without great ruine and wrack, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble cities and townes, and with no leſſe ſpoyle and hauock of infinite goods and riches.</p>
            <p>For like as the deſire to haue dominion ouer many kingdomes, and to haue Soueraingty ouer farre ſtretched Empires, is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon infirmity amongſt Kings &amp; Princes: ſo there is nothing may ſooner prouoke them to giue attempt, then where they ſee ſuch forgetfulneſſe amongſt the people, that ſloath and idleneſſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the whole ſway among them: As <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Apotheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes,</hi> maketh report of a famous captain, to whom a certain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Athemans</hi> made his complaint, that the men of armes in his camp reproched them of <hi>Athens,</hi> to whom the captaine made anſwer, that as the thing that is well kept, is hardly loſt, and that nothing prouokes the theefe ſooner then negligence: So, if the <hi>Athenians</hi> had tyed care and circumſpection to their wordes and deedes, they had neuer falne into the hands of the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16363:22"/>
            <p>And <hi>Cambyſes</hi> the father of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> being asked by what meanes Cities might beſt be kept in ſafety, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, If they that kept the ſame Cities, doe thinke they can neuer be warie inough of their enemies: the which in the <hi>Maſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> was charily performed, who kept both ward and watch in their Cities in the time of peace, as if they had beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually vexed and troubled with warre, and to that purpoſe, inſtituted ſundry good ordinances, vpon the holy dayes to ſee their Souldiours ſtanding vpon the walles, and exerciſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the feates of armes. And that notable Captaine <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paminondas,</hi> whyle the Citizens of <hi>Thebes</hi> gaue themſelues to feaſting, banqueting and bellie cheere, ranne haſtily to arme him ſelfe, and marched towards the citie walles, to the ende the reſt might be the ſafelier drunke, and aſwell to ſignifie, that the ſafety of their Citie ſhould at no time be forgotten.</p>
            <p>And although King <hi>Solomon.</hi> who in the holy Scriptures is called <hi>Rex pacificas,</hi> and was promiſed by the mouth of God a peaceable raigne, and was ſtill buſied, and turmoyled with the building of the holy Temple: yet notwithſtanding, he was not forgetfull to furniſh his garriſons with innumerable men of warre, horſes and chariots. To be ſhort, there is, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath bene any well gouerned Common-wealth, but the lawes of Armes be as carefully prouided for, as any other citie cauſes: but where delicacy once preuayleth and getteth the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, there adew Martiall mindes, and farewell magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, where ſlouthfulneſſe hath once made entrie: for the nobleneſſe that is to be looked for in a princely and hautie courage, though it be chiefly wrought by the force of the minde: ſo the body muſt be exerciſed, and brought in ſuch plight, as it may be made able to follow paine and trauell.</p>
            <p>Were not the old ſouldiours of <hi>Hanniball,</hi> in lying but one winter in <hi>Capua,</hi> ſpending the time in wantonneſſe amongſt the delicate Dames, ſo effeminated and infeebled, both in body and minde, that they neuer did any thing afterward, that was worthy of report.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Xerxes</hi> being offended with the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> becauſe they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16363:23"/>trayterouſly had ſhrunke from him: when he had againe brought them vnder, he forbad them to beare any more weapons, &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commaunded them, that they ſhould ſing to the Lute, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtruments, learne to keepe harlots, and haunt Tauernes, which policy he of purpoſe prepared, to weaken their courages, whereby he might the better keep them vnder awe.</p>
            <p>The knowledge of warre therefore, and the exerciſe of armes are eſpecially to be ſought, neither can I tell whether any thing be more noble, by the which ſo great dominions and noble Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires haue bene purchaſed, Kingdomes enlarged, Princes preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, iuſtice maintained, good lawes protected, and the common wealth defended.</p>
            <p>Great is the glory in the knowledge of warre therefore: neither hath the citie of <hi>Athens</hi> atchieued ſo great renowme and glory, although it merited to bee called the mother of all artes and ſciences, as <hi>Rome</hi> hath done, onely by magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, and force of Martiall might: which brought ſuch reputation to their Common wealth, that farre and ſtrange regions ſought their aliance and friendſhip, and thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues aſſured againſt their enemies, if they had confederation with them, that in the ende, they grew to ſuch admiration, that for their lenitie and ſurmounting curteſie, they were of all men beloued, and for their valiant magnanimitie, they were of all men feared. Neither was this magnificence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden by doing wrong and iniury: for they neuer attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted warres but for things in claime, or in defence of league friends.
<note place="margin">Tull. officiis lib. 1.</note> Then (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth) <hi>The Senate might rather haue bene termed, the protection, hauen, and refuge of kings, people, and nations, more truely then the Empire of the world.</hi> Neither were they found raſh to enter into warres headily, although they had occaſion, as did appeare at the citie of <hi>Sagunto,</hi> where the people of <hi>Carthage</hi> brake the league, and defied peace: yet the Senate ſent thither Ambaſſadour <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> with two tables, the one contal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning peace, the other warres, putting the election to their owne choice, as it is liked themſelues to chooſe, although the Romanes themſelues, could beſt defend their cauſe. But did the Romanes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16363:23"/>game this glory by enuring themſelues to liue in delicate idle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, in dicing, in carding, in dancing, in whoring, in banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in reuelling, and in royſting: no, but ordained moſt ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and bitter puniſhments to expell them, and with diſgrace to dant thoſe that were the practiſers and followers of them.</p>
            <p>Where contrarily, to prouoke and pricke forward Martiall mindes and manly wights, to the ſtudie of chiualry and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall affaires, they ordained glorious triumphs, liberal rewards and honourable titles: which was the very cauſe that the citie grew to be ſo great, and large in Empire: for where valiance and proweſſe was ſo honourably rewarded, not onely Noble men, but alſo inferiour perſons were ſo inflamed with deſire of renowne, that no danger was left vndealt withall, nor no perill left vnproued, where there was glory to be gained, or the ſaftie of their countrie might be preſerued.</p>
            <p>The two <hi>Decit,</hi> by race and birth were no gentlemen borne yet by their valiance and fortitude, they aſpired to the higheſt type of dignitie in their commonwealth, and in their countries defence, conſecrated themſelues, as valiant and vowed veſſells, to glory and immortalitie.</p>
            <p>Neither was <hi>Lucius Martius,</hi> borne but of a meane paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, yet for his puiſſance ſhewed in <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine,</hi> he receiued of his countrie great honour and principalitie.</p>
            <p>By theſe meanes, the libertie of their countries were moſt ſtrongly defended, and the indifferencie of their lawes were chiefly maintained, where well doing is ſo liberally rewarded For what greater diſhonor may there be in a commonwealth then where worthy acts &amp; high attempts receiue but cold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Or what reward, may that country thinke to much to beſtow on him that hath not ſpared his own life to fight in the defence.</p>
            <p>There be ſundry examples in the holy Scripture, tending to the ſame effect, for when the children of Iſrael were purſued by <hi>Pharoh,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they began to ſtagger in the promiſes of God: the tribe of <hi>Inda</hi> did manifeſtly ſhew forth, farre greater courage and valiance then the reſt, who lingred not nor drew
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16363:24"/>backe, but with a maruellous conſtancie, by the example of <hi>Moſes</hi> aduentured firſt the ſea, by whoſe ſtout ſtomaches the reſt were incouraged to follow: For which fact, the people of <hi>Juda</hi> were euer afterwards more honoured then the reſt, and ſuch had the principalitie amongſt the twelue tribes, as were deſcended of the tribe of <hi>Iuda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, <hi>Solomon</hi> made the <hi>Hethites,</hi> the <hi>Amorites,</hi> the <hi>Phereſites,</hi> the <hi>Heuites</hi> and the <hi>Iebuſites,</hi> to become tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and to labour in the building: but of the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, he made men of warre, captaines, great Lords, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Socrates</hi> in a certaine fable vſeth theſe words: <hi>All you that liue in one cittie, are brethren, being ſtreightly linked and vnited together: but when God created you, he gaue not euery one a like propertie, for they that were moſt meete to rule, he tempered with gold: and thoſe that in defence of their countrie would vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly aſſiſt Kings and Princes, he mingled them with ſiluer: and to ſuch as ſhould apply themſelues to tillage and other meane oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations, he beſtowed braſſe and iron: now it falleth out generally that they ingender children like to themſelues: but ſometimes it happeneth a golden father to haue a ſiluer ſonne. He willeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they ſhould take in no one thing, more ſpeciall regard, then diligently to ſearch, with what mettall their childrens mindes bee tempered with, ſo that if there bee found any braſſe or iron in their childrens ſenſes, they ſhould aſſigne them ſuch a trade conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and agreeing with their groſſe and rude nature: but if they finde in them any gold or ſiluer, they ſhould beſtow on them honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable roomes, and that they ſhould be trained vp in the knowledge of Martiall affaires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanes</hi> ordained for that purpoſe, a long ſpacious ſield, which they called, <hi>Campus Martius,</hi> wherein the youth of the citie was exerciſed in Martiall feates, and to enure their bodies, both for their owne health, and alſo that they might be made the more profitable members for their common wealth in the time of warres.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> vſed their children to goe barefooted,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16363:24"/>exerciſing them in running, in leaping, and in caſting the dart, in which exerciſes they were continually practiſed: from whence <hi>Diogenes</hi> on a time returning, and going to <hi>Athens,</hi> was asked from whence he came, and whither he would: I come (ſaid he) from amongſt men, and am going among women.</p>
            <p>I wonder if <hi>Diogenes</hi> were now liuing, and going into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, whither he would ſay he were going, if he were demanded: where we be wholly nuſled in wantonneſſe, and onely nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in daintineſſe, both in minde, manners, and diet: where we be altogether made ſtrangers to Martiall actions, and vtterly alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from Lawes and deedes of Armes, where no conſideration is had of Martiall mindes, where prouiſion for defence is neuer called in queſtion.</p>
            <p>Here peraduenture ſome will ſay vnto me, Good ſir, if you would but put on your ſpectacles, and looke into the Tower of London, you might ſee that neither Ordnance, ſhot, powder, pike, caliuer, armour, nor any other furnitures conuenient for the Warres were any whit lacking: from thence, if it pleaſed you but to ſayle downe in Graueſend Barge, you haue but fiue miles to Rocheſter, where you might likewiſe take the view of ſo worthy a Fleete of royall ſhips, as no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> may make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with the like. Call you not theſe prouiſions of defence, where no munitions fit for the warres are any whit wanting?</p>
            <p>Very true indeede, which doth argue the ſpeciall care his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty hath euer had, not onely in making of ſuch prouiſion, but alſo at ſundry times, he hath likewiſe inſtituted diuers good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances for the training of men, the which hath beene ſtill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continued by his ſubiects, ſuch as will pine at the ſpending of one pound of powder, towards the practiſing of thoſe that ſhould fight for their ſafety.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I neede vſe no other anſwere, then King <hi>Philip</hi> vſed to that noble Captaine <hi>Antipater,</hi> which was this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſeareſt thou man, any Captaine of Athens? Their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and their Peeres are but trifles and toyes vnto me: For what account is to be made of thoſe fellowes that giue themſelues to dauncing, hoyting, banquetting, and to bellie cheare? that if
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16363:25"/>Demoſthenes onely were not amongſt them, I would ſooner get A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens then Thebes or Theſſaly, &amp;c.</hi> So, to what effect ſerue all theſe warrelike furnitures, where there are not men expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced to vſe them; and where men be trained onely in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, how apt be they to endure the perplexities of warre: and how hardly are they faſhioned to the vſe of weapons, that neuer haue had any exerciſe in them, and with what difficultie are they prepared to the field, when they haue neuer beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to march.</p>
            <p>But I haue heard many ſay, that ſouldiers may well be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one moneth, and made fit for the warres, and indeed I I am of this opinion, that he that in one moneth will not learne the vſe of his weapon, whereto he ſhall be ſorted, and to learn to march in order of array, being throughly inſtructed by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and painfull Captaine, I am fully reſolued, that that man wil neuer make good ſouldier. But as our ſouldiers in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are accuſtomably leuied, a Captaine ſhall haue much to do to make a great part of them for euer being ſouldiers at all.</p>
            <p>But admit, that Souldies may be trained and made ready in a moneth, yet during that ſpace, our enemies would commit grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpoiles vpon vs, then we ſhould be able to recouer againe in ſixe weekes after.</p>
            <p>Moreouer in the day ſeruice, I had rather haue one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſuch as haue already ſeene &amp; skirmiſhed with the enemy, then foure thouſand of ſuch haſtie mad ſouldiers, that are but trained vp, as it were at a Midſummer ſight, or at the fetching home of a Maypole. For proofe hereof, I could ſhew many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, but it were but in vaine, conſidering there is no man of reaſon but will conceiue it to be true: and ſuch as haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience will confeſſe I am nothing deceiued in my opinion.</p>
            <p>And to ſay the truth, if in England wee ſhould haue need to vſe any reaſonable number, there would hardly be found conductors, ſuch as be ſufficient in deede for the training of them.</p>
            <p>For Gentlemen that are deſcended of honourable families in theſe daies, giue themſelues rather to become <hi>Battalus</hi> knights
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16363:25"/>then Martiall wights, and haue greater deſire to be practiſed in Carpet trade, then in that kinde of vertue, which extendeth it ſelfe to the common profit, and preſeruation of the Country.</p>
            <p>And I cannot but matuel, what moueth ſo many men to make ſuch great account of their gentility, that they thinke themſelues worthy of ſuch honour and eſtimation: and yet haue no regard to the renowne or prceminence, that is annexed vnto it: for (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) <hi>Truely, the beſt inheritance that Fathers leque to their Children, and more worthy then all aliue, is the glory of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and worthy deedes, whereunto to be a ſtaine, it is to be accounted both vice and ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what reputation bring they to their Houſes, that licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in riot rome to and fto, not knowing in what faſhion to diſguiſe themſelues, what countenance they ſhould beare in the ſtreetes nor with what curioſity they ſhould giue intertainment, furniſhed with three or foure <hi>French, Italian,</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> words, thinking that the whole glory conſiſted in being newfangled in their apparell, ſtrange in their conceits, and as dainty in their diets, as Dame Folly her ſelfe, when ſhee is going of her firſt childe. To be ſhort, in <hi>England</hi> Gentlemen haue robbed our Women of their mindes, and our Women haue bereaued vs of halfe our apparell.</p>
            <p>Where Gentlemen ought rather to indeauour themſelues to ſuch exerciſes of vertuous acts, whereby they might giue ſuch cleare light, and purchaſe true fame to their poſterity, according as their predeceſtors haue left vnto them, of which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues doe ſo mightily boaſt of: and eſpecially, to giue themſelues to ſuch exerciſes, wherein labour prepareth the body to hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the minde to couragiouſneſſe, neither ſuffering the one to be marred with tenderneſſe, nor the other to be hurt with idleneſſe.</p>
            <p>As we reade of <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> who was ſcorned as an effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate King, who chooſe rather to ſit and ſpinne amongſt Women, then to learne to weld weapons: againſt whom, when <hi>Belochas</hi> and <hi>Arbaſes</hi> made inſurrection, he fled, and durſt not ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the field.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16363:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Xenophon</hi> maketh mention how <hi>Hercules</hi> being but a young man, muſing whereunto he might apply his noble minde, there appeared vnto him two goodly young women, the one very gorgious and braue: with ringes on her fingers, a chaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her neck, her haire ſet and frizeled, with pearles and dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds in her eares: the other ſober in her cheere, comely in her apparell, modeſt in her behauiour, ſhamefaſt in her countenance. The firſt ſaid: <hi>Hercules,</hi> if thou wilt ſerue me, thou ſhalt haue gold and ſiluer inough, thou ſhalt feede daintily, thou ſhalt liue Princely, thou ſhalt enioy pleaſures, imbrace delightes, poſſeſſe mirth. In fine, thou ſhalt haue all things to thine owne contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that appertaine to eaſe, reſt and quietneſſe. Then ſpake the other with demure countenance: if thou wilt ſerue me, <hi>Hercules,</hi> thou ſhalt be a Victor of Conquerours, thou ſhalt ſubdue king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and ouerthrow Kings, thou ſhalt be aduaunced vnto fame, renowmed in the world, &amp; ſhalt deſerue praiſe both of man and woman. <hi>Hercules</hi> perceiuing the idle ſeruice of the firſt, and the fame and renowme that was to be gayned by the ſecond, choſe her for his miſtris: &amp; I thinke ſent the other into England, where at this preſent ſhe is duetifully ſerued. But I thinke the very occaſion why many do not indeauour themſelues to practiſe to be ſouldiours now in England, is becauſe they ſee thoſe few that be there already to thriue fo ilfauouredly by their occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they rather ſeeke to indeauour themſelues where there is either pleaſure or profit to be gayned, which is not in Souldiour fare, and therefore makes them to become Courtiers, Lawyers, or Louers. The Court, I confeſſe, is a place requiſite for Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to know, ſo their mindes might not be ſeduced with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities thereof, whereby they ſhould be inticed, not to follow o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſes, tending more to their honor &amp; eſtimation: and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thoſe places, where greater glory is to be gained then any doth ordinarily attaine vnto, that conſumes their dayes wholy in the Court: for he that fully frames himſelfe to become a courtier, muſt likewiſe fraught his head ſo full of courting toyes, that there will be no roome left, to conſider of matters appertaining more to his credit. For the moſt in number of our young courtly. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16363:26"/>thinke that the greateſt grace of courting, conſiſteth in proude and hautie counteuances to ſuch as know them not, to be very faire ſpoken, bountifull and liberall in words to all men, to be curious in cauilling, propounding captious queſtions, thereby to ſhew a ſingularity of their wiſedomes: for the helping whereof, they diligently ſtudie bookes for the purpoſe, as <hi>Cornelius Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa de vanitate ſciuntiarum,</hi> &amp; other like: to ſeeme to talke of farre &amp; ſtraunge countries, of the maners of the people, of the fertilitie of ſoyles, &amp; by the way of communication, able to diſpute of all things, but in deed to know nothing, to apply their pleaſant wits to ſcofting, quipping, gybing, and taunting, whereby they may be accompted merry conceited gentlemen, and withall, they muſt learne to play the paraſites, or elſe I can tell them, they will neuer learne to thriue. And in their apparell, they muſt be very nice &amp; neat, with their ruffes finely ſet, a great bundle of feathers thruſt into a cap, which muſt like wyſe be of ſuch a bigneſſe, that it ſhall be able to hold more wit then three of them haue in their heades.</p>
            <p>They muſt be raſh in their iudgements, curious in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, they muſt be bold, ſaucie, and mallapert, which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues terme to be good audacity. They muſt be ready to eſpy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans faults, but not to ſee their owne folly. But what ſhould I ſtand to deciphre the vanities of our courtiers, which are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſo painted foorth in their colours, and that by ſo many men, as I do but waſt the time in vaine about them: I doe likewyſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that the law is eſpecially to be practiſed by Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. For as the law it ſelfe is moſt honourable amongſt men: ſo thoſe that ſhould be practiſers, profeſſours, and miniſters of the lawes, ought likewyſe to be of credit and eſtimation.</p>
            <p>But our Innes of court in theſe dayes are ſo furniſhed with Shomakess ſonnes, Taylers ſonnes, Inholders ſonnes, Farmers ſonnes, and almoſt there is not ſo meane a man, but his ſonne muſt goe to the Innes of court: and they, when they haue gotten a litle law, becauſe they will not mend ſhoes, and doe as their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done before them, there is no ho in their getting, no meaſure in their taking, no meane in their brybing, nor no reaſon n their extorting.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16363:27"/>
            <p>Theſe be they, that by Law will peruert Law, and what one Law doth make, they will bring another Law ſhall marre. Theſe be they that laugh, when other men mourne and that make themſelues rich, by other mens follies: and theſe be the onely men that bring Law and Lawyers into ſuch Exclamations.</p>
            <p>But of all other people that doe moſt ſurmount in vanities, are thoſe that in ſuch contagious paſſions, conſume their time in loue, that as <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> doth affirme, he that doth once fall in loue with another, doth euen then beginne to hate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It hath many times been had in queſtion, from whence the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this malady ſhould ſpring: but the greateſt part doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the originall thereof doth proceede of idleneſſe.</p>
            <p>Loue where it once taketh hold, it tormenteth the patiente with ſuch ſtrange and bitter paſſions, that it reduceth reaſon into rage, pleaſure into paine, quietneſſe into carefulneſſe, mirth into madneſſe, neither maketh it any exceptions of perſons, either old or young, rich or poore, weake or ſtrong, fooliſh or diſcreet, that as <hi>Peter Bouayſtuan,</hi> a notable French Authour doth write, that if all the Louers that are in the World, were made in one whole Army, there is neither Emperour, nor Monarch, but would be amazed to ſee ſuch a company of Bedlem fooles in a cluſter.</p>
            <p>But he that ſhould take the view of their countenances, geſts, manners, furies, and all their franticke toyes, might confeſſe that he neuer ſaw a more ſtrange Metamorphoſis, or a ſpectacle more ridiculous to laugh at. If at any time they haue receiued a merry countenance of their beloued, good God, how gay ſhall you ſee them in their apparell, how chearefull in their countenance, how pleaſantin their conceits, how merry in their moodes: then they bathe in brookes of bliſſe, they ſwimme in ſeas of ioy, they flow in flouds of felicity, they houer all in happineſſe, they flie in ſweet delights, they baniſh all annoy.</p>
            <p>Contrarily, if they receiue a lowring looke, then you ſhall ſee them drowned in dumpes, they plead with piteous plaints, they cry with continuall clamours, they forge, they faine, they flatter,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16363:27"/>they lie, they forſweare, other whiles falling into deſperate moodes, that they ſpare not to blaſpheme the Gods, to curſe the Heauens, to blame the Planets, to raile on the deſtinies, to cry out vpon the furies, to forge hell, to counterfet <hi>Siſiphus,</hi> to play <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talus,</hi> to faine <hi>Titius,</hi> to grone with <hi>Prometheus,</hi> to burne the Winter, to freeze the Summer, to loath the night, to hate the day, with a thouſand other ſuch ſuperſtitious follies, too long for me to rehearſe.</p>
            <p>Now if he be learned, and that he be able to write a verſe, then his Pen muſt ply to paint his Miſtreſſe praiſe, ſhee muſt then be a <hi>Pallas</hi> for her wit, a <hi>Diana</hi> for her chaſtity, a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> for her face, then ſhee ſhall be praiſed by proportion: firſt her Haires are wires of gold, her Cheekes are made of Lillies, and red Roſes, her Browes be Arches, her Eyes Saphires, her lookes lightnings, her mouth Corall, her teeth Pearles, her paps Alablaſter balles, her body ſtreight, her belly ſoft, from thence downe ward to her knees, I thinke is made of Sugar Candy, her armes, her hands, her fingers, her legges, her feete, and all the reſt of her body ſhall be ſo perfect, and ſo pure, that of my conſcience, the worſt part they will leaue in her, ſhall be her ſoule.</p>
            <p>But what neede I heape vp ſo many words in this matter? My Pen hath not the power to paint their doting deuiſes: neither doe I minde otherwiſe then to wiſh, that Gentlemen ſhould ſet aſide all ſuch trifling affaires, and vaine follies, and to ſhake off thoſe delightfull deſires, and rather to indeuour themſelues to ſuch exerciſes, which haue gained <hi>Hercules, Achilles, Theſeus, Caius, Marius, Epaminondas, Themiſtocles, Alexander, Pyrrhus, Hannibal, Scipio, Pompey, Caſar,</hi> with diuers others, ſuch immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall glory, as neither the enuious rage of cruell death may ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, neither the furious force of Fortunes fickle wheele may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, neither the tract of deuouring time ſhall euer be able to remoue from memory. And I would to God, that while time doth yet ſerue vs in <hi>England,</hi> that ſuch care might be had for the training and practiſing of men, that we ſhould not be found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſo careleſſe, that to ſatisfie all our voluptuous pleaſures, we neuer conſider the preſeruation of our Country and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16363:28"/>wealth. So likewiſe, if it be not altogether too late, as I feare me it is, I would wiſh that another thing were looked vnto, and that very narrowly, wherein we haue made ſuch a rodde for out owne tayles, as there is no queſtion, but in the end it muſt of force fall out to be our owne ſcourge. And this it is: We had in <hi>England</hi> ſo great a benefit, as it might haue beene vſed, as no other Countrey inuironing about vs, is poſſeſſed with the like, which is the caſting of yron Ordnance: but as the prouerbe is, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry commodity bringeth his diſcommodity, ſo this commodity bringeth vs double diſcommodity. Firſt in the caſting, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth vs our woods and timber, in ſuch ſort, that one of the firſt things that <hi>England</hi> ſhall want, will be of timber for ſhips, which is all made hauocke on, onely about thoſe yron mils. In the end comes M. Merchant, who cares not (for his owne priuate gaine) what miſchiefe he worketh to his Countrey: or ſometimes ſome olde bruiſed ſouldier, that hath ſerued the Queene in her warres, about <hi>London, Lambeth</hi> Marſhes, or the out ſles of Iſlington, all the dayes of his life, and in reſpect of his good ſeruice, muſt get a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to ſell two or three hundred pieces of this yron Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance out of the Realme, that between M. Merchant and him, I dare vndertake, there is thrice as much Ordinance ſold out of the Realme, as is within the Realme, and that ſome of our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants haue felt. For <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman hath been at Hoſt with ſome of their ſhips, and Dauy Drunkard of Fluſhing, and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, haue not been behind: and theſe with other mo, were not able to goe ſo ſtrongly to the Sea, were it not that they were fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with our Engliſh Ordnance. The Spaniards and Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals haue ſome pretty ſtore of it. In <hi>France</hi> there is <hi>Rochel, Roſco, S. Mallous,</hi> and <hi>Deepe,</hi> their ſhips be generally as well ſurniſhed with our Ordnance, as any Merchants ſhips in the Thames. The mighty Hound of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nkerke, and the reſt of the Beagles that were of her conſorts, God knowes, had beene able to haue made but a ſlender cry, when they had come to chaſe, had it not beene for our Engliſh barkers. The other parts of <hi>Flanders, Zeland,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> both vpon the walles of their Townes, and alſo in their ſhipping, are furniſht with the like. I haue ſeene euery ſtreete in Fluſhing, lye as full of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16363:28"/>Engliſh Ordnance, as if it had beene the Tower Wharfe of London. To be ſhort, there are diuers Townes in Eaſt <hi>Freeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with <hi>Emden, Hambrough, Denmarke, Danske, Lubecke, Rye, Reuell, Swethen,</hi> with diuers other Cities and Townes of thoſe Eaſt parts, that ſhe is but a very meane Hulke, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to any of theſe places, which hath leſſe then a dozen or ſixteene peeces of our Engliſh Ordnance in her.</p>
            <p>Such hath beene the careleſneſſe of this our peaceable time, that it hath not onely made vs weake, by our owne neglecting the feates of armes: but alſo with our owne artillerie, and our warrelike munitions, we haue made ſuch ſtrong as be our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as I feare we ſhall finde, if they were at quietnes amongſt themſelues.</p>
            <p>And thus once againe I can wiſh, that ſuch conſideration might be had of the time that is preſent, as in the time that is to come, we ſhould not haue cauſe to rue it.</p>
            <p>And here although I know my skill will not ſerue me, nor my occaſion at this time may well permit me, to ſpeake of Martall diſcipline, how farre it is decayed from the firſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and inſtitution, yet gentle Reader, not doubting but thou wilt beare with me, as well for the want of the one, as for the neceſſitie of the other, I will aduenture to ſpeake ſome thing thereo.</p>
            <p>We doe find in holy Scriptures, and that in ſeuerall places, both in the bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the booke of <hi>Joſua</hi> and others where they haue vſed no litle regard as well in chuſing of their captaines, leaders, and conductors, as alſo in their preſcribing lawes, and diſciplines of warre, which were many times ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the almightie God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But let vs peruſe the examples of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which of all other people did moſt exceed, as well for the greatnes of their glory, as in all their other martial actions, and we ſhall find that they had not only conſideration to the equitie of their cauſe for the which they would enter into wars (as by theſe words of <hi>Tully,</hi> in his 1. book of <hi>Offices</hi> may better appeare: <hi>And the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of warre is moſt ſincerely deſcribed in the Pheſiall Law of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16363:29"/>people of Rome, whereby for things in claime, is moued, or elſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimea before, and bidden by deſiance, &amp;c.</hi>) But alſo they had as great regard to maintaine their quarrels, with like equitie and iuſtice, not ſuffering their captaines to enter into actions of treaſon or trecherie where their wars were al together arreared vpon cauſes of honeſtie, as by examples they did plainly ſhew.</p>
            <p>When king <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> vnprouoked had moued wars againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Timochares</hi> whoſe ſonne was yeoman for the mouth to the king, promiſed to <hi>Fabrieius</hi> then being Conſull, to ſlay king <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> which thing being reported to the Senat, they preſently warned king <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> to beware of ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſaying, The Romans maintained their warres with armes and not by treaſon or trechery.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, when <hi>Lucius Pius</hi> in a banquet that he made, had filled the people of <hi>Samaria</hi> full of wine, and made them ſo drunke, that yeelded themſelues ſubiect to <hi>Rome,</hi> for which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit <hi>Lucius Pius</hi> at his returne required triumph. But the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators vnderſtanding the manner of his fact, cauſed him open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be beheaded, and a ſlanderous Epitaph ſet vpon his graue. Neither would they ſuffer that ſouldier, which amongſt other being taken by <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and licenced vpon his oath to deprrt, conditionally that he ſhould either make returne, or elſe ſend his ranſome, the ſouldier with others of his companions, being departed the campe of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and licenced vpon his oath to depart, conditionally that he ſhould either make returne, or elſe ſend his ranſome; the ſouldier with others of his companions, being departed the campe of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> feigned an arrand back againe for ſomething that he had forgotten, and thus comming to <hi>Rome,</hi> did thinke himſelfe diſcharged of his oath: but the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate allowing of no ſuch d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceit to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evſed, made a decree that the ſame Souidier ſhould be carried pinioned to <hi>Hannibal.</hi> And ten other, that in like manner were diſmiſſed by <hi>Hannibal,</hi> vpon their oth were ſeſſed at a yeerely fine, as long as any of them did liue for being forſworne. So nobly were the <hi>Romans</hi> diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo honourably minded, that no act was allowed of amongſt them, ſeemed it neuer ſo profitable, wherin was found
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16363:29"/>either fraude or deceit. And this magnificence, gate them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne commendations of their very enemies, and betweene whom there had beene mortall hoſtilitie, and many times was of greater effect to ſubdue them, then huge or mighty armies. And as they did excell in the excellency of theſe vertues, iuſtice and equity, to ſuch as were able to ſtand in armes againſt them: ſo likewyſe they did ſurmount in humanity and curteſie, and in miniſtring of comfort, to ſuch as they had already vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ſubdued, as by no example may be better expreſſed, then, by a letter written by <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> to <hi>Popilio,</hi> captaine of the <hi>Parthies,</hi> a notable diſcourſe for captaines to peruſe, and foloweth in this manner. 
<q>
                  <p>I cannot denie the glory I haue gained by this battell, neither may J hide the perplexitie I feele for thy preſent miſfortune: for noble mindes are bound to ſhew no leſse compaſſion, to ſuch as are ſubdued, then to expreſſe toy and gladneſſe with thoſe that are victors. Thou being the chiefe of the Parthies, dideſt ſhew great courage to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist, and in me the leader of the Romanes, was found no want of force to fight: notwithſtanding, though thou loſt the battell, and J remaine poſſeſſed of the victory, yet as I know, that thou wilt not acknowledge this chance to happen for any want of ſtomach in thee, ſo it belongs to my grauity not to attribute it altogether to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my vertue, ſithens God doth alwaies miniſter victories, not to ſuch as doe their duties beſt, but to thoſe that he loueſt moſt: for the effect of all things de pending vpon God, man can haue no power to command the deſtiny of a battell, ſeeing he is not able to ſtay the courſe of the leaſt planet in Heauen. <hi>Darius</hi> againſt <hi>Alexander, Pompeius Caeſar, Hanniball</hi> againſt <hi>Scipio,</hi> had aboue all equality farre greater Armies then their enemies, by which thou haſt reaſon to conclude with me, that againſt the anger of the ſoueraigne God, cannot preuaile moſt huge and mighty Hoſts. J maruell <hi>Popilio,</hi> that being great in birth, valiant of ſtomach, welthy in goods, and mighty in eſtate and dignity, why thou beareſt with ſuch ſorrow, the loſſe of this battell, ſeeing that in no worldly things Fortune is more vncertaine and variable, then in the action of Warre. It is tolde me, thou draweſt to ſolitary corners, and ſeekeſt out ſhaded
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16363:30"/>places, thou eſcheweſt the conuerſation of men, and complaineſt of the gods, which extreame perplexities ſince thou wert not wont to ſuffer in others, much leſſe oughteſt thou to giue place in thy ſelfe: For that the valiant man loſeth no reputation, for that Fortune faileth him, but is the leſſe eſteemed of, if he want diſcretion to beare her mutability.</p>
                  <p>To aſſemble great Armies, is the office of Princes, to leauy huge treaſures, belongs to ſoueraigne Magiſtrates, to ſtrike the enemy is the part of a couragious Captaine: but to ſuffer infirmities, and to diſſemble miſhaps, is a property duely annexed to noble and reſolute mindes ſo that one of the greateſt vertues that worldly men can expreſſe, in the common behauiour of this life, is neither to riſe proud by prosperity, nor to fall into despaire by aduerſity. For Fortune hauing a free will, to come and goe when ſhee liſt: the wiſe man ought not to be ſorry to loſe her, nor reioyce to hold her. Such as in their miſery ſhew heauy countenance, doe well proue, that they made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to be alwayes in prosperity, which is a great folly to thinke, and no leſſe ſimplicity to hope for: Seeing the giſts and graces of Fortune haue no better thing more certaine in them, then to be for the moſt part, in all things moſt vncertaine, according to the ſucceſſe of the day, wherein thou gaueſt me battell: for there thou orderedſt thy Campe according to a wiſe Captaine, madeſt choyce of the place, in great policie, tookeſt aduantage of the Sunne, as a leader of long experience, in conſideration of which things thou haſt cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine againſt thy Fortune, which fauoured not thy vertue, and not blame thy diſcretion, wherein could be found no errour.</p>
                  <p>Conſider that in wiſe and graue men, it is an Office, that if they cannot doe what they will, at the leaſt they yeeld to time, and are content with what they may. And as the vertuous and valiant minde ought not to grieue for not obtaining that which hee would, but becauſe he deſired that which he ought not: ſo <hi>Popilio,</hi> I wiſh thee take heede, that the honour which ſo many times thou haſt won, with the hazard of thy valiant perſon, in enterpriſes of warre, be not loſt at this preſent, for want of bearing well thy Fortune: aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thee, that he beares his miſery beſt, that hides it moſt. And as of all valuble things, there is nothing more light then renowne:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16363:30"/>ſo in caſes of warre and hazard, it is not enough for the valiant man to doe what he may, but alſo hee is bound to attempt nothing but what he ought: For as well the conſideration as the execution of a fact, belongs duely to a diſcreet minde.</p>
                  <p>I heare thou wandereſt here and there in great vncertainty of minde, fearing that if thou be taken of my Souldiers, thou ſhalt be euill intreated of me, which if no man haue told thee, it is againſt reaſon thou beleeue it of thy ſelfe, becauſe to vs Princes of Rome, it is familiar to ſhew our liberality to ſuch as yeeld to vs, and with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are our priſoners to communicate in great clemency. We raiſe armies againſt Campes proudly furniſhed, and Cities ſtrongly walled, but to captiues in thy condition, wee hold it more honourable to miniſter comfort, then to adde increaſe of affliction. For as it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth the valiant Captaine to fight againſt the enemy that reſiſteth him, and diſſemble with him that flieth: ſo the wiſe man ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no more of his enemy, then that he acknowledge that he ſtands in feare of him, becauſe to a daunted and timorous heart, is ſildome left courage to renue a enterpriſe. And therefore a man takes greater reuenge, when he putteth his enemy to flight, then if he take his life from him. For the ſword dispatcheth a man in a day, but feare and remorſe torments the minde continually. And better it were to ſuffer without feare that which we expect in griefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, then by feare to be alwayes in martyrdome. It is right terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fleſh and bloud to die of a ſword, but to be in perpetuall ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and diſquiet of minde, is the very furie and torment of Hell.</p>
                  <p>If thou eſcheweſt my preſence, in feare that I will not vſe pitty to thee, thou art abuſed in the opinion of my dispoſition, and doſt wrong to the reputation and experience of my actions paſt. For J neuer refuſed to ſhew merey to him that asked it, and much leſſe deceiuéd him that put his truſt in me. The doubt and feare that thus doe trauell thy minde, ought not to be ſo much of my perſon, as of the cuſtome of Fortune, who vſeth not to vnloſe her ſharpe Arrowes with better will againſt any then ſuch, as thinke they bee in beſt ſecuritie of her: her nature being ſuch, as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16363:31"/>not to meddle with thoſe that ſhee finds prepared, the better to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, but followeth the fearefull and negligent, to the end to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them: yea, ſhee preuailes turn ouer the counſels and actions of men, and being exempt to make reckoning to any, her prerogatiue is to require account of all men. I aſſure thee <hi>Popilio,</hi> that more doe I feare the reuolution of fortune at this houre, then I doubted her before the battell. For ſhee delights not ſo much to keepe vnder the vanquiſhed, as to bridle and checke the victors. And worſe doth ſhee meane, when ſhoe ſmiles the faireſt, then when ſhee frownes moſt. But to ſpeake on thy behalfe, J tell thee that without danger thou maiſt reſort to my preſence, ſince in thy ſtate is no cauſe of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, and in my heart no malice to thy perſon: for indeede, that cannot be called true victory, which bringeth not with it ſome cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency. And therefore he cannot be called victorious, in whom reſteth intent of rigour and cruelty. For <hi>Alexander, Iulius, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, Titus,</hi> and <hi>Traianus,</hi> won more renowne by the clemency they vſed to their enemies, then by all the victories they obtained in ſtrange regions. To obtaine a victory is a thing naturall and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, but to giue pardon and life, is the gift and bleſſing of God. By which it comes to paſſe, that men feare not ſo much the greatneſſe of the immortall God, for the puniſhments he doth, as for the mercy he vſeth. Notwithſtanding as I cannot denie, but that great is the value and eſtimation, which we Romane Princes make of a victory won by battell: ſo alſo J aſſure thee, we hold it more honourable, to pardon ſuch as doe offend vs, then to chaſtice thoſe that doe reſiſt our power.</p>
                  <p>Therefore if thou flie from my preſence, as fearing the iuſtice which I haue executed vpon the Romanes, thou oughteſt to take ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity and courage euen in that which makes thee iealous and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: for ſo much greater ought to be clemency, by how much the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender is in fault. And therefore as there is no offence which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be either forgiuen or fauoured, ſo right worthily may that pardon be called honourable and famous, which is giuen to an iniury mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and manifeſt, ſince all other common and light wrongs with greater reaſon we may ſay we diſſemble them, then that wee pardon them.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:16363:31"/>
                  <p>The thing that moſt drawes me to enter friendſhip with thee, is for that in our firſt capitulations and truce, thou performedſt all things that were concluded for the peace, and yet in the battell thou didſt expreſſe the parts of a valiant Captaine, the ſame giuing me cauſe to beleeue, that as in warre I found thee a iuſt enemy, ſo in the time of peace, thou wouldeſt proue an aſſured friend. <hi>Alexander</hi> neuer repented the pardon he gaue to <hi>Diomedes</hi> the tyrant, nor <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> the fauour he ſhewed to the great Orator <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero.</hi> Neither ſhall I haue cauſe (I hope) to forethinke the reſpite I giue to thy liife. For the noble minde, albeit he may haue occaſion to be ſorry for the vnthankefulneſſe of his friend: yet hath hee no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to repent him of his good turnes done for him: and therefore in the caſe of liberality or clemency, by how much the perſon is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy that receiueth the benefit, by ſo much more hee is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended that beſtoweth it: for that onely may be ſaid is giuen, when he that giueth, giueth without respect.</p>
                  <p>So that hee that giueth in hope of recompence, deſerueth not to be called liberall, but to pretend vſurie.</p>
                  <p>Thou knoweſt well that in the time of the battell, and when the incounter was moſt hot, J offered thee nothing worthy of reproach: euen ſo, thou haſt now to iudge, that if in the fury of the warre, thou foundeſt me faithfull, and mercifull, I haue now no reaſon to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe rigour, holding thee within the precinct of my houſe: ſo that if thou ſaw mercy in me at that inſtant, when thy hands were buſie to ſpill my bloud, thinke not that my clemency ſhall faile, calling thee to the fellowſhip of my Table.</p>
                  <p>The priſoners of thy Camp can aſſure thee of my dealing, amongſt whom the hurt are cured at my charges, and the dead are buried according to the place of ſouldiers: wherein if I extend this care vpon ſuch as ſought to ſpoile me, thinke there is farre greater plenty of grace, to thee that commeſt to ſerue me. And ſo leauing thee in the hands of thine owne counſell, I wiſh thee thoſe felicities, which thy houourable heart deſireth.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Lochere a mirrour, meete to be peruſed by Kings and Princes, wherein they may learne, with what conſideration they ſhould firſt enter into Warres, with what valiance and courage they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16363:32"/>ſhould proſecute them, and with what iuſtice, temperance and mercie they ſhould vſe their enemies.</p>
            <p>Captaines may likewiſe learne how to vſe fortune, either when ſhe fauours, either when ſhe frownes,</p>
            <p>But leauing a great number of neceſſary leſſons worthy to be noted, how is it poſſible in ſo few lines, more amply to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the glory of the <hi>Romones:</hi> neither are their vertues here ſo liuely painted foorth in words, as they themſelues did nobly ſhew it in their deedes.</p>
            <p>But all other examples of humanity, amongſt a great number vſed to their enemies, this in my opinion deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the leaſt commendation, that hauing taken <hi>Siphax</hi> King of <hi>Numantia,</hi> who being kept priſoner in the houſe of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> dyed of ſickneſſe before he was ranſomed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding now when there was no manner of hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall, his funeralles were yet performed, with ſuch ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſuch pompe, and ſuch honour, ſuch large giftes were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſuch liberality vſed, being but a <hi>Romane</hi> priſoner, as might haue wanted at <hi>Numantia,</hi> where he was Lord and King ouer all. I haue thus farre briefly, and in this ſhort maner ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome part of the magnificence of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> in their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall actions, whereby may be perceiued, how farre we be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and how cleane we be degenerate at this preſent from their honorable inſtitutions. For if we conſider in theſe dayes the impiety that is found amongſt Princes, which for the moſt part are ſo led by the furie of ambition, where they thinke they may oppreſſe, that without any other reſpect of cauſe they are ready to accompanie themſelues, with a ſorr of bloody cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, that ſhould haue the leading of a company of as lewd &amp; vngratious ſouldiers, and euen according to their quarrels and to the quality of their owne diſpoſitions, they proſecute their warres, and performe all their enterpriſes, the which for the moſt part are executed with ſuch treaſon and trecherie, as no Prince almoſt may be ſo ſurely garded, but his life ſhalbe fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with ſome deadly blow with a weapon, with ſome ſodaine ſhot of a piſtoll, or at the leaſt practiſed with ſome ſecret poiſon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16363:32"/>nether is there any town, that may be ſo ſurely walled, ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered, or ſo throughly fortified which ſhall not be betraied.</p>
            <p>For in our warres we be now come to this paſſe, that fraud and deceit is reputed for policy, and treaſon and trechery are called grauity and wiſedome, and he is holden the nobleſt cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, that by any of theſe meanes can beſt deceiue: where, in the opinion of all men, which exactly do honor iuſtice, it hath euer beene condemned, and accompted moſt horrible. And no doubt it can not be acceptable in the ſight and iudgement of God, who in the Scripture is called the God of trueth and verity: but rather proceedeth from the deuill, who is (indeede) the father of fraude, and the forger of all deceite.</p>
            <p>And theſe enormities haue euer beene eſpecially practiſed amongſt thoſe that haue arreared warres, rather to oppreſſe and, rauiſh the goods of others, then amongſt ſuch as haue but defended their owne right, or entred into warres onely vpon cauſes of iuſtice and equity, for that it hath bene euer holden a matter moſt inconuenient, rather by ſubtilty to vndermine, then by force to conquer.</p>
            <p>Now for the incitements to valour, there is no motiue more mighty to incite men to valour and courage, then when they ſhall call to minde the rightnes of theirs: the which doth ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and ſet an edge on their hearts, according to the opinion of <hi>Cicero,</hi> who affirmeth that manlineſſe is well defended of the Stoiks, which is a vertue that is a Champion of equity, wherefore no man hath euer attained to the honour of forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or get praiſe by policy. For nothing is deemed honeſt that is deuoyde of Fuſtice: he likewiſe maketh a further procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the ſame place, reciting the ſaying of <hi>Plato</hi> to the ſame effect, that ſcience not accompanied with conſcience &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge diſioyned from iuſtice, is rather ſubtilty then ſolid wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; thoſe enterpriſed which are vndertaken for our owne profit, and not the weale publick is more truely termed fooliſh hardineſſe then famous valour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristotle</hi> would by no meanes that <hi>Diomedes</hi> ſhould bee reputed either wyſe or valiant, for that when feare had made
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16363:33"/>wings for the Grecians heeles, and they were diſcomfited in fight, he ſtill continued fight in the field, and aduentured him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to incounter with <hi>Hector,</hi> with more audacity and courage; then vnderſtanding and conſideration, more reſpecting the bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of fame and vaine praiſe of men, the which though for a time it may ſeeme delightfull, yet is but of ſhort continuance, when the ſafety of his ſoyle and commodity of his Countrey, the which is the ſcope of all vertuous actions, and an immortall glory.</p>
            <p>In ſuch ſort he cenſured <hi>Hector,</hi> who many times caſting vp his eyes to his wife, and other Women ſtanding vpon the walles of Troy, would with greater courage and audacity aduenture and hazard his life, onely to gaine fauour and reputation in the Womens opinions, and fearing leaſt any rumour ſhould berai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed which might wound his credit, when otherwiſe hee would haue had a more reſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e care of his life: They are therefore farre remote from the renowne of true valour, which will ſo raſhly runne vpon their owne ruines without any due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate premeditation, for what auailed the audacity of <hi>Varro</hi> and <hi>Flaminius,</hi> two renowned Romane Captaines, who reiecting the proweſſe, and contemning the craft of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing the counſell of <hi>Fabius,</hi> firing the anchor of their hope in their owne hardineſſe, endangered and ruined two noble armies, whereby the power of the Romanes lay a bleeding, and was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vtterly periſhed: It is a common receiued opinion, that a man cannot attaine to the exact perfection of the meaneſt occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation vnder ſeauen yeeres practiſe, and doth it ſtand with like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood? nay, hath it almoſt any poſſibility, that the art of Warre ſhould be ſo ſuddenly wonne, wherein there is alwayes a <hi>Plus vltra,</hi> and a furthermore. For they which haue all the courſe of their life beene followers of that courſe, and haue continued the faithfull men of <hi>Mars,</hi> they haue not proceeded ſo farre, but ſtill they might goe one degree further, and haue beene to ſeeke in ſomething: this was the matter which moued <hi>Philip</hi> to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, that the Athenians did yeerely chooſe new Generals and Captaines of their warres, when hee in the whole courſe of his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16363:33"/>life had found one worthy of his approbation, which was <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menio; Plato</hi> would not allow any man authoritie in <hi>Mars</hi> his imployments, till he was thirty yeeres of age: and <hi>Alexander</hi> would admit none to the place of a commander vnder ſixtie: finally by the generall conſent and confirmation of al men, there ought not to be a ſlight or ſmall reſpect vſed in the choice of Captaines. <hi>Cicero</hi> mentioneth foure things requiſite in a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the warres, to wit Iuſtice, Fortitude, Policie and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance: Firſt, Iuſtice to reuenge, Fortitude to put his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in execution, Policy to prepare the way to leade him to his ends, and temperance to ſtay him in his fury, when he hath ſufficiently diſcharged it vpon his enemies; and it is free from doubt, and certaine without ſuſpition, that a Captaine thus endowed with theſe vertues, ſhall be of no ſmall preuailance in all his proiects, but they haue very little reſpect of any of theſe in the election of our Engliſh Souldiers, who are appointed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to maſter Conſtables command, and who if he hath taken a diſtaſt, and conceiued a diſpleaſure againſt any in his circuit, cannot excogitate a better meanes to vent his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or thinke of a ſpeedier courſe to oppreſſe him then to preſſe him forth to be a Souldier: but if he chance to be in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with his neighbours, then doth he ſelect ſome ſilly odde fellow that doth leaſt good in the pariſh, as who ſhould ſay, he cannot be too bad to be a Souldier, and for the moſt part they ſcoure their priſons of theeues, and their ſtreets of rogues and vagabonds when they are to ſet any Souldiers forth, ſo that they ſeeke ſuch men for ſuch imployments as were better loſt then found. I heſe are the authors and fountaines from whence ſuch abuſes flow, and the cauſers of a Souldiers name to bee ſo odious to the vulgar and common people: and another diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity hath birth from the preſſing of ſuch a ribble rabble, for in the warres they become mutiners, who ought to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with no ſmall ſeuerity for infringing the inſtitutions, and violating the orders of the generall Captaine, the which how diſtaſtfull it is to God, the puniſhments which God hath inflicted vpon ſuch perſons may ſufficiently teſtifie in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16363:34"/>booke of Numbers it is recorded, that the earth opened and ſwallowed vp <hi>Corath, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abyram,</hi> for mutining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> an euident and apparant proofe, how diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Almightie theſe kinde of inſertions be, and that they are rebels to God that reſiſt their Captaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Manlius Torquatus</hi> ſhewing more ſeuerity then affection, cauſed his owne naturall ſonnes head to be moued from his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe he remoued out of the place whereto he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; notwithſtanding hee went out of it to fight with an enemy, who had formerly challenged him. And <hi>Saluſt</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that there were more ſouldiers ſuffered for aſſaulting there enemies before they had command from the Captaine, then for running out of the field before the combat, who were very ſeuere in inflicting heauy puniſhments on ſuch like offenders, and to the end that they might the better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect Souldiers to their diſcipline, adioyned to their owne Lawes the authority of God, and were accuſtomed with great ceremonies ſolemnly to ſweare them to obſerue their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. <hi>Cicero</hi> recordeth how <hi>Pompilius</hi> when he was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Romans in the Perſian warres, had diſcharged one legion in which <hi>Catos</hi> ſonne had ſerued for a Souldier, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was diſcharged, yet ſtill continued there, being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſee the warres, which <hi>Cato</hi> vnderſtanding, did write to <hi>Pompilius</hi> that he ſhould not permit or ſuffer his ſon to remain or abide in the army, vnleſſe he did ſweare him Souldier againe, becauſe otherwiſe it was vnlawfull for him to fight with the enemy, for being freed from his former oath, hee was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſcharged from being a Souldier: it was a generall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome amongſt the Grecian to ſweare there Souldiers being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and brought to Church in this manner. I will not doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing vnworthy the ſacred holy warres, neither will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh or forſake my Captain to whom I am appointed; I wil not be the cauſer of my countryes illfare, but I will to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt bounds of my abilitie and limits of my power indeauour that it may reape all poſſible benefits by my ſeruice, and I will continually frame and faſhion my ſelfe to the obedience and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16363:34"/>obſeruance of ſuch orders, as are now or ſhall be hereafter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by the ſtate. Moreouer as I will neglect them my ſelfe ſo farre as I am able force others to keepe them. I will perpetually maintayne and retayne the religion of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, the which my promiſes I call the Gods to record and witneſſe: the which cuſtome if it were now obſerued and put in execution amongſt ſouldiours in our times, it could not but be a meanes to ſecure their Generall and gouernour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them to the vndertaking of all worthy enterpriſes, be an Antidote and preſeruation agaynſt ſuch treacheries as are dayly practiſed, and would in like manner gaine credit and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>All which things are manifeſted in that true mirror of true worth <hi>Count Manſfield:</hi> who as he hath kept their ſeruice free from mutiny ſeuerely, ſo he hath rewarded his ſouldiours bountifully, which hath ſo animated them, and giuen them life in all their proceedings, that they haue with matchleſſe courage performed all their enterpriſes: And <hi>Manſfield</hi> the generall of there army, hath had no leſſe then generall applauſe: who to his eternall memory and neuer dying fame, hath enlarged his owne renowme, made an addition, eſpecially to his reputation by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſtant to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and a moſt worthy main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of the Goſpell of Chriſt: of whoſe worthy actions if I ſhould indeauour to make a particular diſcourſe, it would farre exceed the power of my pen: and I am affraid, I ſhould wrong him in the relatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: and I ſeare, in this more laſciuious then la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious age, he wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcarce attayne to the happineſſe of <hi>Achilles</hi> to haue a ſecond <hi>Homer,</hi> to trumpet forth the trueth of his worth, who hath all the vertues lodged in his breſt, that can be imagined to be reſident in a Prince or ſouldiers boſome: For as he htah couragious valour, denying to permit him to carry coales or ſuffer exceſſe of iniury, ſo he hath a meaſure of honeſt policy to performe what he proiecteth, and leaſt there might be any defect in him vndeſeruing the name of a Captaine, or a Commaunder, like a ſecond <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> he is ſo well furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with perſwaſiue oratory, that the ſoules of his ſouldiours
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16363:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>in time of his exhortation to him, ſeeme onely to be placed in their eares, and his very breath is a wynde to blow, (as I may ſo ſay) the coales of their courage and to accend their fury: For at what time as he obtained the famous victory againſt <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus</hi> before <hi>Hguenae,</hi> he moued his ſouldiours in a well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſpeach, to behaue themſelues boldly and with courage, and to make a full expreſſion of their valour, ſince that they were to haue ſuch a noble compagnion in combate as the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who was royally reſolued to purſue his foes in perſon.</p>
            <p>I neede not therefore ſeeke farre for a Commaunder, whoſe example may ſerue for euery captaines inſtruction, who as he ſhould looke for duety from them in his ſeruice, ſo ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord them meanes whereby they may liue (as they are to be truely conſidered) profeſſours of a worthy calling: he ſhould likewyſe incourage them with mouing ſpeeches, incite them to valour and noble actions. To conclude, a true ſubſtantiall ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour, and a gainefull generall, ought to be powerfull in men and meanes, politick in plotting meanes aſwell for the defence of himſelfe as the offence of his enemy, royall in rewarding in the well-deſeruing, eloquent in perſwading his men to proweſſe: So ſhall the warres be more proſperous, the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours more reſpected, and a happy ſucceſſe ſhall crowne all Marſhalliſts earneſt indeauours.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
